<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>travel on Micro-optimist</title>
    <link>http://alanbernstein.github.io/tags/travel/</link>
    <description>Recent content in travel on Micro-optimist</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 01 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="http://alanbernstein.github.io/tags/travel/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Hypercorrection</title>
      <link>http://alanbernstein.github.io/posts/hypercorrection/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://alanbernstein.github.io/posts/hypercorrection/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t like to be &amp;ldquo;that guy&amp;rdquo;, correcting meaningless mistakes of grammar/usage/pronunciation in conversation, because for whatever reason it&amp;rsquo;s considered rude or thoughtless. But if the mistake you&amp;rsquo;re making is &lt;a href=&#34;wikipedia&#34;&gt;hypercorrection&lt;/a&gt;, pointing that out must be&amp;hellip; hypocorrection? Which, by extrapolation, must then be polite and thoughtful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite my belief that prescriptivism in language is useless, it still feels grating to my ears when I hear incorrect usage. I don&amp;rsquo;t care about being right, or winning an argument about it, I just care about the truth being known. So, I don&amp;rsquo;t bring it up in person. But that doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean I won&amp;rsquo;t write about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Around 2012 I started noticing people pronouncing the word &lt;em&gt;processes&lt;/em&gt; as &amp;ldquo;processEEZ&amp;rdquo; instead of &amp;ldquo;processIZ&amp;rdquo;. As far as I am aware, there is no rule of English pronunciation that says to do this. I think what happened is that someone misremembered the rule for pluralization of -x words, and started applying it all over the place like a crazy person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be specific:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most words are pluralized by appending the letter &amp;ldquo;s&amp;rdquo;, which is pronounced as &amp;ldquo;z&amp;rdquo;, like in &amp;ldquo;birds&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Singular words ending in one &amp;ldquo;s&amp;rdquo; are pluralized by adding &amp;ldquo;es&amp;rdquo;, which is pronounced as &amp;ldquo;iz&amp;rdquo;, like in &amp;ldquo;buses&amp;rdquo;. Words ending in &amp;ldquo;sh&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;ch&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;se&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;z&amp;rdquo; are treated similarly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The fairly unusual case: words ending in &amp;ldquo;x&amp;rdquo; are &lt;em&gt;sometimes&lt;/em&gt; pluralized by adding &amp;ldquo;es&amp;rdquo;, which is pronounced as &amp;ldquo;ih-sees&amp;rdquo;, like in &amp;ldquo;matrices&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This third case only applies to certain words ending in &amp;ldquo;x&amp;rdquo;. For example, &amp;ldquo;thorax&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;vortex&amp;rdquo;, and &amp;ldquo;matrix&amp;rdquo; are pluralized with the third rule, but &amp;ldquo;climax&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;complex&amp;rdquo;, and &amp;ldquo;fix&amp;rdquo; are pluralized with the second rule. I can imagine that this is determined by etymology, but I don&amp;rsquo;t see an obvious pattern.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clearly, not even all &amp;ldquo;-x&amp;rdquo; words use the &amp;ldquo;ces&amp;rdquo; spelling and &amp;ldquo;ih-sees&amp;rdquo; pronunciation. So, I found it pretty confusing when I started hearing words that don&amp;rsquo;t even end in &amp;ldquo;x&amp;rdquo; being pluralized this way as well. This appears to be a perfect example of hypercorrection to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If that&amp;rsquo;s not convincing enough, consider these other examples, none of which are usually pluralized with the third rule.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Words ending in &amp;ldquo;ss&amp;rdquo;: embarrass, mass, cross&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Words ending in &amp;ldquo;ess&amp;rdquo;: congress, dress, press, goddess, mattress&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Words ending in &amp;ldquo;cess&amp;rdquo;: success, excess, access, recess, princess&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that as this list progresses, the suffix match with &amp;ldquo;process&amp;rdquo; increases in length.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Processes&amp;rdquo; should be pronounced &amp;ldquo;processIZ&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Upgrading my bike accessories</title>
      <link>http://alanbernstein.github.io/posts/bike-microoptimization/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Mar 2021 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://alanbernstein.github.io/posts/bike-microoptimization/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve always been fond of physical modular systems, but lately I&amp;rsquo;ve become a little obsessed with customizing my stuff with modular attachments. My bike has seen the most of this, both in terms of the number of projects, and the amount of effort put into them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-organizer&#34;&gt;The organizer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much of this is built around Ortlieb bike accessory products, which I have committed to as a sort of &amp;ldquo;platform&amp;rdquo; for durable, hackable bike accessories. I like Ortlieb&amp;rsquo;s roll-top, rain-proof panniers, but the lack of built-in organization is frustrating. I started with a custom internal organizer sleeve, which includes a laptop pocket, and some webbing for organizing other smaller items, especially my bike lock. This was a major project, which required learning how to sew and design fabric patterns, among other things. A project log is &lt;a href=&#34;ortlieb-organizer&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I write this, nearly a year after completing the v2 organizer, I notice that Ortlieb now has a &lt;a href=&#34;https://ortliebusa.com/product/commuter-insert-for-panniers/&#34;target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;commuter insert&lt;/a&gt; product. If this had existed 18 months ago, I likely would not have bothered making my insert, but I prefer my design for several reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The organizer sleeve, as well as several other components, are made possible with Fidlock magneto-mechanical quick-release devices. These are kind of the ultimate quick-release solution; the magnets bring the two halves together with very little manual alignment needed, closing a latch, which provides a sturdy mechanical connection. They can then be separated with an action that is unlikely to happen on accident - pulling in a specific direction, pressing a button, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-dog-basket&#34;&gt;The dog basket&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After concluding that my dog Gizmo hated riding in a doggy backpack, I started putting him in a basket on my rear rack, which he loves. At first, I attached a milk crate to my rack with zip ties. This worked fine while in use, but it prevented me from attaching the Ortlieb panniers, so I would have to remove it after every use. Obviously what I needed was a quick-release mount. Trolling Craigslist for &amp;ldquo;ortlieb&amp;rdquo;, I eventually found &lt;a href=&#34;https://ortliebusa.com/product/adapter-for-travel-bikerbike-box23shuttleoffice-bag2-with-lock-e174/&#34;target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; device, which attaches to the top of any rack, and provides a QR mechanism for mounting a trunk bag or a basket. The &lt;a href=&#34;https://ortliebusa.com/product/adapter-for-rear-basket/&#34;target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;other half&lt;/a&gt; is available separately for $10, so I got a couple of those for experimenting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(aside) Ortlieb has an even better rack-top QR system called &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ortlieb.com/usa_en/service/technical/rack-lock&#34;target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;rack lock&lt;/a&gt;. Unfortunately, the mechanism does not seem to be available stand-alone. I&amp;rsquo;m not willing to buy a $150 bag just for the mechanism, especially when I actually want several of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the metal tubing that comes with this thing is not well-thought-out. The idea is that it provides a horizontal bar for your pannier to clip onto, since the QR base is covering the rack. Great, except the new bar is two or three inches lower than the rack, which just doesn&amp;rsquo;t work, because it puts the panniers too low on the bike. I had a self-defeating QR system; the base had to be installed and uninstalled each time. It&amp;rsquo;s also a very frustrating install process (unsupported discrete nuts instead of integrated female threads), so this had to be solved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I got aluminum tubing and a bender, and made a rounded square to replace the crazy-shaped tubing. Now, everything works well enough. There is still one problem: the tubing goes out a little too far, which makes it difficult to attach the bottom latch of my panniers. But, generally, it works. Also, since I don&amp;rsquo;t normally ride with the dog basket attached, I can use the QR base to attach other things. I&amp;rsquo;d like a small trunk bag, maybe just big enough to hold a lock, some snacks, and an insulated water bottle. I haven&amp;rsquo;t figured out how to do that yet, but I have created an &lt;a href=&#34;TODO&#34;&gt;attachment for a U-lock&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for the dog basket, the milk crate still works great. I improved it by added some padding to the bottom and the rim, plus a liner made out of a blanket. I designed an origami pattern that converts a square blanket into a box with a padded bottom and four sides. The idea is that, in the crate, the blanket can serve as the bottom padding, the liner, and the retainer ties for the rim padding, while out of the crate it can serve as a picnic blanket. It turns out that folding an origami pattern in a blanket is kind of a hassle, so I&amp;rsquo;d like to sew some color-coded velcro guides onto the blanket.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[TODO gizmo pic]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;other-upgrades&#34;&gt;Other upgrades&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above two projects were relatively major, requiring significant design, specialty parts, fabrication, and iteration. After using them for a few months, I realized that I have been failing to apply my hobby of micro-optimization to my bike. With a box of leftover Fidlock clasps, I started noticing more small improvements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fidlock squeeze buckle for helmet (for one-handed closing while riding)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fidlock v-buckle for pannier (for one-handed closing while riding)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;External organizer with Fidlock button-latch&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even more upgrades:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mylar strip replacement for flimsy fabric that holds top pannier buckle (prevents falling in an annoying space between the pannier and the rack) &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thingiverse.com/thing:4091748&#34;target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Someone else&amp;rsquo;s solution&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Waterproof QR seat bag to replace my old, disintegrating, non-water-proof bag&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rear light attached to helmet in a fully modular, replaceable way (TODO photo)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Permanently-mounted, minimal, DIY rear fender (TODO photo)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rei.com/product/718391/sks-beavertail-fenders&#34;target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Removable front fender&lt;/a&gt;. I was planning to design and build my own until I found this, which took a surprising amount of searching. There are many variations on the removable bike fender, but this is the only one I know of that provides full protection, and has a sturdy mount.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Had to design and print a tool: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thingiverse.com/thing:4831058&#34;&gt;https://www.thingiverse.com/thing:4831058&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/bike-microoptimization/IMG_5258.25&#34;
        alt=&#34;Overview&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;&#34;
        alt=&#34;laptop sleeve insert&#34;/&gt; - link to blog post&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/bike-microoptimization/IMG_5252.25&#34;
        alt=&#34;Fidlock helmet latch&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/bike-microoptimization/IMG_5???.25&#34;
        alt=&#34;Fidlock helmet latch attached&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/bike-microoptimization/IMG_5254.25&#34;
        alt=&#34;Fidlock v-buckle v1&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/bike-microoptimization/IMG_5272.25&#34;
        alt=&#34;Fidlock v-buckle v2 construction&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/bike-microoptimization/IMG_5276.25&#34;
        alt=&#34;Fidlock v-buckle v2&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/bike-microoptimization/IMG_5260.25&#34;
        alt=&#34;Side-mounted mini pack&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/bike-microoptimization/IMG_5268.25&#34;
        alt=&#34;Side-mount closeup&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/bike-microoptimization/IMG_5263.25&#34;
        alt=&#34;Side-mount male&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/bike-microoptimization/IMG_5266.25&#34;
        alt=&#34;Side-mount female&#34;/&gt; - magnetic QR key&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/bike-microoptimization/IMG_5261.25&#34;
        alt=&#34;Ortlieb QR seatbag&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/bike-microoptimization/IMG_5270.25&#34;
        alt=&#34;QR rack mount&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- replace with the new aluminum one
TODO

metalwork pics
![AR dog basket](https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/bike-microoptimization/IMG_5???.25)


![U-lock rack mount](https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/bike-microoptimization/IMG_5269.25)
--&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lies, Damned Lies, and Exponentials</title>
      <link>http://alanbernstein.github.io/posts/exponential-crusade/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://alanbernstein.github.io/posts/exponential-crusade/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;An exponentially increasing blog post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It bugs me when people misuse the term &amp;ldquo;exponentially bigger&amp;rdquo;, often just comparing two numbers. To describe the growth of something as exponential, more than two numbers &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; be taken into account (unless you somehow have evidence that the underlying process is itself exponential, which is generally not the case in random charts and quotes found on the internet). Exponential growth is a &lt;em&gt;trend&lt;/em&gt;, a constant multiplicative factor over the independent variable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m sure this point has been made a million times by other nerds. I noticed a related point recently which is a bit more subtle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;example-1-appropriately-emphasizing-a-true-outlier&#34;&gt;Example 1: Appropriately emphasizing a true outlier&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A coworker shared &lt;a href=&#34;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/EUm-p1AXkAwHpVs?format=jpg&amp;amp;name=medium&#34;target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;this tweet&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/exponential-crusade/tweet-1-chart&#34;
        alt=&#34;Figure 1: Chart of unemployment spike&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then noted&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;maybe they should have used a log chart&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Noting the excuse from the article:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;The linear scale shows the real human impact &amp;ndash; a growth twice the size is twice the number of real people infected.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I responded&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;as a mathy person i scoffed at this, but i guess they have a point&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a technical person, it&amp;rsquo;s easy for me to forget that a log-scale plot might be more difficult to interpret than a linear-scale plot. Particularly with a bar chart, where the filled rectangles make up shapes, which are often interpreted in charts based on their relative area. Showing relative size in an immediately-interpretable way can have its value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trend here isn&amp;rsquo;t exponential. It&amp;rsquo;s a true spike, so presenting it in a way that emphasizes that makes sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;example-2-inappropriately-hiding-small-details&#34;&gt;Example 2: Inappropriately hiding small details&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another time, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/chsrbrts/status/1320012627947540480&#34;target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;this tweet&lt;/a&gt; was shared:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/exponential-crusade/tweet-2-chart&#34;
        alt=&#34;Figure 2: Chart of NLP parameter growth&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;This slide puts into context how big of a step forward GPT-3 is in the field of natural language processing.&amp;rdquo;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I responded:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;my pet peeve: failure to use log scale when appropriate&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then made a log-scale chart and shared it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/exponential-crusade/nlp-chart-log&#34;
        alt=&#34;Figure 3: Chart of NLP parameter growth, log scale&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So someone responded:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;that kind of defeats the purpose of the chart which is to show the massive difference. I think it has more impact the other way, though the log scale certainly gives more visual information about the differences between all the others&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which, of course, is the same argument I just explained above. I said:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sure, the purpose of the tweet is to point out the difference, which is essentially just saying 175B vs 17B. The chart itself is pointless because you can&amp;rsquo;t get any information from the bars, you have to read the numbers instead. Without a log scale, it&amp;rsquo;s just a very poorly formatted table&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what I should have said was this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tweet tries to make a claim with a linear-scale chart of a trend that is fundamentally exponential.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you look at the record-breaking y-values, excluding the latest one, and extrapolate vs time, the expected y-value is something like 70B, vs actual 175B. This is 2.5X jump over the expected value. Previous high-outliers were something like 8B when 5B was expected, a 1.6X jump. 175B is a LOT of parameters, and a 2.5x jump over the expected value is big, AND it&amp;rsquo;s the biggest jump. But it&amp;rsquo;s not a MIND-BLOWING jump that justifies a chart that totally obscures this historical development by hiding all of the details behind a linear scale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Fundamentally exponential&amp;rdquo; seems reasonable, like many things in the computing world. But is it true? Yes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/exponential-crusade/nlp-chart-log-time.png&#34;
        alt=&#34;Figure 4: Chart of NLP parameter growth, log scale vs time&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why Benford&#39;s Law is Obvious</title>
      <link>http://alanbernstein.github.io/posts/benford/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://alanbernstein.github.io/posts/benford/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Benford%27s_law&#34;target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Benford&amp;rsquo;s Law&lt;/a&gt; states that in many naturally occurring collections of numbers, the leading digit is likely to be small. I love math factoids like this, and I remember how deeply unintuitive this seemed when I first learned it. Now, I find myself looking for a way to explain how intuitive it really is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;tldr&#34;&gt;TL;DR&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, Benford&amp;rsquo;s law isn&amp;rsquo;t obvious. But what would the world look like if it were?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Benford&amp;rsquo;s law follows unavoidably from a certain type of probability distribution (uniform in the logarithmic domain), which happens to be common in real-world data. I can draw some charts that &amp;ndash; to me &amp;ndash; make this perfectly clear. Somehow, that doesn&amp;rsquo;t make it any less surprising to learn. Go figure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I contend that the surprise comes from a lack of familiarity with the log-uniform distribution. What if we, as a society, internalized that distribution &lt;em&gt;instead&lt;/em&gt; of the &amp;ldquo;usual&amp;rdquo; linear-uniform one? In this post, I explain what the counterpart of Benford&amp;rsquo;s law would be in that case. It turns out, it&amp;rsquo;s almost too obvious to mention. Which is the point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;benfords-law&#34;&gt;Benford&amp;rsquo;s Law&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you first hear of it, the thinking might go something like this: if you choose a number randomly, shouldn&amp;rsquo;t the first digit be uniformly distributed? Even if the original distribution isn&amp;rsquo;t uniform, as long as it covers a wide enough range, why would the &lt;em&gt;first digit&lt;/em&gt; have any bias?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Explanations abound, but I find that they often miss the crucial point (like this otherwise fantastic &lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/etx0k1nLn78&#34;target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;video&lt;/a&gt; for example). Simply put, it is a direct consequence of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reciprocal_distribution&#34;target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;log-uniform distribution&lt;/a&gt;, which governs these &amp;ldquo;naturally occurring collections of numbers&amp;rdquo;, e.g. measurements, population counts, etc. If you can accept that these natural collections tend to be log-normal distributed, Benford&amp;rsquo;s Law is &amp;ldquo;obvious&amp;rdquo;, that is, an unavoidable consequence. Some simply explain this empirically, giving examples. But I think there is more to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why do some collections of numbers have this tendency? I like to think of it like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The logarithmic scale is &lt;em&gt;at least&lt;/em&gt; as natural a way to look at the world as the linear scale is.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In a given scale (linear, log, or otherwise), a uniform distribution is the &amp;ldquo;simplest&amp;rdquo; option. It&amp;rsquo;s sort of a default distribution, perhaps in part due to being the maximum entropy distribution for a bounded domain.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m aware that this is an academic viewpoint - I&amp;rsquo;m using &amp;ldquo;obvious&amp;rdquo; facetiously here. While the log-uniform distribution may be more &amp;ldquo;natural&amp;rdquo; in some sense, the linear-uniform distribution is certainly not unusual. Roll a die, draw a card, pick a ball from an urn - these are all basic processes, easily understood, and obviously uniform. While they may be more common in the built environment rather than in nature, they are still regular occurrences to a human child living in society, helping to reify the linear scale in her mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The linked video also presents a counterexample to Benford&amp;rsquo;s law, plus a counterpart law with its corresponding counterexample. Paraphrased:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Benford&amp;rsquo;s Law: most-significant digits are expected to be biased toward lower values with a logarithmic trend, &lt;em&gt;if&lt;/em&gt; the range of values spans multiple orders of magnitude.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Benford Counterexample (Biden votes): If the data spans just a single order of magnitude (specifically [10^n, 10^(n+1)) so the number of digits is constant, then the first-digit distribution just reflects the data distribution itself. Benford&amp;rsquo;s law is not &lt;em&gt;violated&lt;/em&gt;, it is rather &lt;em&gt;not applicable&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last-digit test: least-significant digits are expected to be distributed uniformly, &lt;em&gt;if&lt;/em&gt; the range of values is wide enough, relative to the precision of the values.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last-digit counterexample (incumbent votes): If the data spans just a single, &lt;strong&gt;low&lt;/strong&gt;, order of magnitude, e.g. [10, 100), then the last two digits are just &lt;em&gt;the digits&lt;/em&gt;, so the last-digits distribution just reflects the data distribution itself. The last-digit test is not &lt;em&gt;violated&lt;/em&gt;, it is rather &lt;em&gt;not applicable&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a pleasing sort of duality here, and illustrating each of these with the two political parties&#39; vote counts is pretty cute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;another-counterpart&#34;&gt;Another counterpart&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although these are interesting lines of thought, they prompted another question, the real motivation for writing this: is there &lt;em&gt;another&lt;/em&gt; counterpart to Benford&amp;rsquo;s Law, which might be equally surprising to a culture that thinks in the logarithmic scale by default? Of course, human sensory perception is logarithmic, as is our natural perception of integers. But early education beats that out of us, and our culture generally encourages us to consider the linear scale as the default way of thinking about numbers - the Way Numbers Really Are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If, instead, we were trained from a young age to think about the logarithmic scale as the default, then what sort of distribution would lead to a similarly surprising result, and what would that result be?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After ruminating on this topic over the years, and a concerted hour or two of trying to answer this question, I found a candidate. I&amp;rsquo;ll restate Benford&amp;rsquo;s again for comparison:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Benford&amp;rsquo;s Law: When accustomed to the linear scale, a log-uniform distribution results in a suprising bias in first-digits, logarithmically decreasing from 1 to 9.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the linear counterpart:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Drofben&amp;rsquo;s Law: When accustomed to the logarithmic scale, a linear-uniform distribution results in a surprising bias in number-of-digits, exponentially increasing from 1 (to N).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These charts illustrate both laws, as described above &amp;ndash; but I&amp;rsquo;ll elaborate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;graphical-explanation-benfords-law&#34;&gt;Graphical explanation, Benford&amp;rsquo;s Law&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/benford/figure1.png&#34;
        alt=&#34;Figure 1: Log-uniform random data&#34;/&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Figure 1: Log-uniform random data&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a set of three views of the same random data set, following a log-uniform distribution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1a shows that log-uniform data follows a logarithmically-decreasing trend, &lt;em&gt;when viewed in the linear domain&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1b shows that log-uniform data follows a constant trend, when viewed in the (arguably more appropriate) logarithmic domain.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1c shows Benford&amp;rsquo;s law directly, with bar heights corresponding to first-digit bias. Note that this shape closely resembles the shape of the distribution in 1a &amp;ndash; it isn&amp;rsquo;t identical, because 1c kind of &amp;ldquo;layers&amp;rdquo; the histograms from each level of magnitude in 1a, into a new form that examines only first digits instead of all values.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1d (aside from being kind of busy because I&amp;rsquo;m a bad graphic designer) shows where these &amp;ldquo;layers&amp;rdquo; come from. The black trace represents the determinstic values of the function first_digit(x) for all values of x in [1, 10000]. The green regions cover all numbers that start with 1, and they&amp;rsquo;re widest &amp;ndash; that cumulatve width corresponds to the height of the bar for digit 1 in figure 1c. Red regions correspond to numbers that start with 2, with a more moderate cumulative width. Purple corresponds to 5, with a much smaller width, and similarly for all other digits.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This figure explains why Benford&amp;rsquo;s Law is &amp;ldquo;obvious&amp;rdquo;. It may be more clear to explain the logical progression of thought:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This data follows a natural distribution &amp;ndash; log-uniform &amp;ndash; illustrated by the constant trend in the logarithmic domain (1b).&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This necessitates a logarithmic-decreasing trend in the linear domain (1a).&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This necessitates a logarithmic-decreasing trend in the first digits (1c, 1d).&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;graphical-explanation-drofbens-law&#34;&gt;Graphical explanation, Drofben&amp;rsquo;s Law&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And here are the corresponding charts for Drofben&amp;rsquo;s law:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/benford/figure2.png&#34;
        alt=&#34;Figure 2: Linear-uniform random data&#34;/&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Figure 2: Linear-uniform random data&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a set of three views of another random data set, following a linear-uniform distribution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2a shows that linear-uniform data follows a constant trend, when viewed in the linear domain.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2b shows that linear-uniform data follows an exponentially-increasing trend, when viewed in the logarithmic domain.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2c shows Drofben&amp;rsquo;s law directly, with bar heights corresponding to number-of-digits bias. Note that this shape closely resembles the shape of the distribution in 2b.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2d shows the analogous &amp;ldquo;layers&amp;rdquo; of Drofben&amp;rsquo;s law &amp;ndash; these layers just represent magnitude. The gray region, representing numbers with five digits, takes up 90% of the total width. Pink, for four digits, takes 9%, and so on.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the second case, these layers just reflect the counts of integers in ranges: |[1, 10)| = 9, |[10, 100)| = 90, |[100, 1000)| = 900, etc &amp;ndash; this seems almost too obvious to mention. But, that&amp;rsquo;s what I was looking for &amp;ndash; a result that&amp;rsquo;s surprising to an alien, logarithmic culture &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; be obvious to our linear minds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(&lt;a href=&#34;https://gist.github.com/alanbernstein/39cc97fc582cbb2cd30df59c40853129&#34;target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;code for charts&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-digits-are-not-the-value&#34;&gt;The digits are not the value&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/benford/treachery-of-digits-hex.png&#34;
        alt=&#34;The treachery of digits: an homage to Magritte&amp;amp;rsquo;s The Treachery of Images, with &amp;amp;ldquo;This is not a number&amp;amp;rdquo; as a caption for the hexadecimal representation of the floating-point value NaN, &amp;amp;ldquo;Not a Number&amp;amp;rdquo;&#34;/&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The treachery of digits, with apologies to &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Treachery_of_Images&#34;target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Magritte&lt;/a&gt;&amp;hellip; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NaN&#34;target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;IEEE&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;admonition warning&#34; style=&#39;border-left:4px solid #cd5f3c; padding-left:2em; font-size:16px; margin:2em 0&#39;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;title&#34;&gt;Warning&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;content&#34;&gt;Philosophical rambling ahead&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this might seem silly. Consider a linear-uniform distribution over [1, 100). Of course the range [10, 99] is 10x as likely as the range [1, 9] &amp;ndash; that&amp;rsquo;s just the relative size of the intervals. But it&amp;rsquo;s the &lt;em&gt;arithmetic size&lt;/em&gt;, the linear size. If you were conditioned to think first of the &lt;em&gt;geometric size&lt;/em&gt;, the logarithmic size, you would instinctively see these two intervals as having (nearly) the same size. You wouldn&amp;rsquo;t expect the linear-uniform distribution, and this behavior would indeed be surprising. Perhaps it&amp;rsquo;s hard to imagine this, because &lt;em&gt;the digits themselves&lt;/em&gt; make it obvious: for Benford&amp;rsquo;s Law, it is not obvious that 1234 is any more likely to occur than 5678. In contrast, you can&amp;rsquo;t help but notice that 5 has only one digit, while 5678 has four digits. However, considering non-integer values allows us to make a more illustrative comparison between 5.678 and 5678. Try to imagine perceiving numbers through their &lt;em&gt;magnitude&lt;/em&gt; instead of their &lt;em&gt;digits&lt;/em&gt;. Perhaps growing up using a slide rule is the best way to internalize the logarithmic scale. I missed that boat by a few years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My point is, the digits are only a representation of the number&amp;rsquo;s value. Despite being a perfectly complete representation, the &lt;em&gt;digit string&lt;/em&gt; is not an innate property of the &lt;em&gt;value&lt;/em&gt;, but rather an artifact of the representation system. It&amp;rsquo;s like looking for information in the pixel boundaries of a photograph: anything you find might be explained by the sampling grid, and disappear under a different sampling. Any properties of the digit string of a number might be explained by the choice of base, and disappear under a different base.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, the number of digits is a crude approximation of the magnitude (regardless of the choice of base), whereas the first digit is more reasonably described as a &amp;ldquo;random&amp;rdquo; artifact of the representation. I&amp;rsquo;ll concede that the number of digits is not &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; an artifact, and therefore Drofben&amp;rsquo;s Law is more obvious &amp;ndash; &lt;em&gt;if&lt;/em&gt; you think about numbers primarily in terms of their non-fractional digits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;admonition note&#34; style=&#39;border-left:4px solid #3c5f8d; padding-left:2em; font-size:16px; margin:2em 0&#39;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;title&#34;&gt;Tangent&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;content&#34;&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m a former mathlete, I love recreational math problems/puzzles. These sometimes concern properties of the base-10 representation of numbers (Project Euler often uses the &lt;a href=&#34;https://projecteuler.net/problem=20&#34;&gt;digit sum&lt;/a&gt;, etc., similarly, the Putnam exam usually includes a problem where the current year is used as an &lt;a href=&#34;https://kskedlaya.org/putnam-archive/2019.pdf&#34;&gt;upper limit&lt;/a&gt; or the like), and I&amp;rsquo;ve always thought of these as sort of &amp;ldquo;impure&amp;rdquo; problems which aren&amp;rsquo;t as deeply interesting. On the other hand, there is some deep math involved in &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Goodstein%27s_theorem&#34;&gt;Goodstein sequences&lt;/a&gt;, based on fiddling around with hereditary base-N notation. Although, it comes specifically from &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; constraining N.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;base-effects&#34;&gt;Base effects&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When working with numbers, we have to pick some representation system; base 10 is fine, but it might be interesting to think about how these artifacts change when using different systems. While Benford&amp;rsquo;s Law occurs regardless of the base, there is some interesting behavior at the extremes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;base 2: Benford&amp;rsquo;s Law doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean as much in this case &amp;ndash; all first bits are 1! The generalization still applies to first-N-bits, but this is still an interesting comparison. In contrast, number-of-bits is now a closer approximation to the magnitude of the number.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;base infinity: each numeral is represented by a different symbol. Now, number-of-digits is always 1! Most of the questions become meaningless, because we&amp;rsquo;ve abandoned the concept of place-value digits, without abandoning the values. The concept of &amp;ldquo;first digit bias&amp;rdquo; isn&amp;rsquo;t even tautological as in the base-2 case. The distribution of digit occurrences still contains some information, however.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aside from these extremes, there is the zero-padded representation of base-N. Now, regardless of the the value of N, first-digit is uniform, and number-of-digits is constant. As lazy humans, we don&amp;rsquo;t bother writing out all these leading zeros, but that&amp;rsquo;s how computers work! I suppose a child raised by computers would think all of the zero-pad-counterparts of these laws are perfectly obvious and devoid of value.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ortlieb Organizer</title>
      <link>http://alanbernstein.github.io/posts/ortlieb-organizer/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://alanbernstein.github.io/posts/ortlieb-organizer/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Project log for my organizer insert for Ortlieb Back Roller bike panniers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-1&#34;&gt;
Current status
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
https://ortliebusa.com/product/commuter-insert-for-panniers/&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
v1.2, in active use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
TODO:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;attach more nylon webbing, for attaching other accessories to the side of the insert&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;sew new version with flaps that cover the frame pockets&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;record a video of the quick-release action&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/PXL_20210124_174351054.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/PXL_20210124_174351054.jpg&#34; title=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/PXL_20210124_174351054.jpg&#34; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Mounted to bag. Photographing this thing is tricky.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/PXL_20210124_174448037.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/PXL_20210124_174448037.jpg&#34; title=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/PXL_20210124_174448037.jpg&#34; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Fidlock magnetic QR mount, female side, mounted to exterior of insert&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/PXL_20210124_174506005.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/PXL_20210124_174506005.jpg&#34; title=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/PXL_20210124_174506005.jpg&#34; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Fidlock magnetic QR mount, male side, mounted to interior of Ortlieb bag&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-2&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-2&#34;&gt;
Iterations
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-2&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-3&#34; class=&#34;outline-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-3&#34;&gt;
v1.2: Add magnetic quick-release mount
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-3&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At this point, it works well enough that it has become part of my normal bike kit. Since I&amp;#39;m working from home until the apocalypse is over, I&amp;#39;m stopping here for now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-4&#34; class=&#34;outline-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-4&#34;&gt;
v1.1: Ripstop nylon, retrofitted with the through-the-frame lock mount
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-4&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One nice thing about sewing is that the stitching step is reversible. After learning from v2, I decided that I prefer the thinner nylon fabric, but the through-frame U-lock mount works much better than the surface-stitched version. So, not having any more fabric, and not having easy access to my laser cutter due to covid, I unstitched the first strap, and retrofitted the through-frame mount onto this bag.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-5&#34; class=&#34;outline-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-5&#34;&gt;
v2: Canvas, first version that &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; works (2020/05/09)
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-6&#34; class=&#34;outline-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-6&#34;&gt;
v1: Ripstop nylon, first minimally viable version (2020/02/25)
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-6&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having a decent idea what the pattern should be, it was now feasible to laser cut it. I cut these out:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nylon: 2x base, 2x tall, .5&amp;#34; seam margin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canvas: 2x base, 2x tall, 1&amp;#34; seam margin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I chose to start with an all-nylon bag. I realized later I might have used canvas for the outside and nylon for the inside. All-nylon was a good choice to start with though.
I sewed the nylon pieces together, knowing that it would be easier to sew the other bits on first, but not knowing exactly where to put them. The fabric was thin enough that I could manipulate it enough to sew things on later. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-7&#34; class=&#34;outline-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-7&#34;&gt;
v0.2: random scrap fabric, pattern test (2020/01/25)
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-7&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
After the cardboard prototype, I decided I was ready to take on the sewing project. I bought some off-the-shelf fabric that seemed appropriate, and then proceeded to think about how to make the thing for a few months. I spoke with some very helpful people at the Sew and Tell meetup, and finally accepted that I just need to try making it a few times. One of the suggestions was to make that first fabric prototype with cheap scrap fabric, so I tried that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The design was based on the cardboard model, with two broad sides and a thin strip connecting them to give it some volume. I got one big design suggestion at the meetup that allowed me to make progress on this: each side should have a sealable pocket to contain the plastic insert. With that in mind, this first version allowed me to test cutting the pattern, and the sewing process. It turned out that this fabric was awful to work with (very stretchy and very ragged edges), but I definitely learned enough to gain the confidence to work on the next version, with the good fabric.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/2020-01-25 21.38.14.50.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/2020-01-25 21.38.14.50.jpg&#34; title=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/2020-01-25 21.38.14.50.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I was proud of myself for documenting my learning process with the first bag, but it was not that helpful afterward. I changed the design, and I&amp;#39;ve already internalized the lessons I learned about sewing techniques. Probably most significantly, I abandoned the side strip idea. A laptop fits inside the bag without that added width, and I had a hard time keeping the three pieces of fabric properly aligned. I might want to use a similar approach for a different project later. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Lessons learned:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Began to understand how to think about designing the inside-out object.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When my mental model of the inside-out object fails, I can pin fabric together and turn it inside out to test.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When sewing around a corner, and you need to raise the foot to reposition the work piece, you can rotate it in &lt;strong&gt;either&lt;/strong&gt; direction - it doesn&amp;#39;t have to follow the direction of the seam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I try the thin strip idea again in the future, I will cut it maybe four inches longer than needed, THEN sew it, then trim excess. That will fix half of the alignment problem, but still need to be sure that the two side pieces are lined up properly. It might be easier to use several smaller thin strips, but that would also be uglier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When cutting the pattern, following the curved corners isn&amp;#39;t important: cut a polygonal hull, sew whatever seam you want, then trim. The seam doesn&amp;#39;t even need to be curved, because the bag will take on an organic shape anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The four main parts are attached with three seams, and I put the third one in the wrong place, so the first two were unnecessarily exposed. It occurred to me that I could have just used a single seam, but having multiple seemed like a good idea anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-8&#34; class=&#34;outline-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-8&#34;&gt;
v0.1: cardboard and zip ties, proof-of-concept (2019/02/25)
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-8&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first attempt was a cardboard mockup, held together with zip ties. This worked well enough to prove the concept. It disintegrated after a month or so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/IMG_20190224_215759905.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/IMG_20190224_215759905.jpg&#34; title=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/IMG_20190224_215759905.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/IMG_20190224_225931398.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/IMG_20190224_225931398.jpg&#34; title=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/IMG_20190224_225931398.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-9&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-9&#34;&gt;
Sewing process
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-9&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 19.06.12.50.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 19.06.12.50.jpg&#34; title=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 19.06.12.50.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Latest prototype in action. The two main features driving the structural design are the laptop pocket and the U-lock strap.
I&amp;#39;m a sewing beginner, and this is my first design, so I&amp;#39;m learning, making things up as I go, and I probably don&amp;#39;t know a lot of terms that I should. Despite that, I&amp;#39;m very satisfied with this second iteration. It&amp;#39;s truly usable, but I hope to refine it, so I&amp;#39;ll point out a few issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 19.05.29.50.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 19.05.29.50.jpg&#34; title=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 19.05.29.50.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It goes inside this popular Ortlieb pannier. I&amp;#39;m avoiding any permanent modifications to the waterproof exterior. Still figuring out mounting options, but that&amp;#39;s not a major concern, because normally the bag is full enough to keep the organizer in place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 18.57.34.50.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 18.57.34.50.jpg&#34; title=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 18.57.34.50.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
My three prototypes: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Orange: random scrap fabric, to experiment with the basic pattern, not really usable &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blue: random ripstop nylon (specs unknown, but it&amp;#39;s .1mm thick). Includes a sewn-on nylon strap to hold the lock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yellow: random canvas (.6mm thick). Includes a &amp;#34;through-the-frame&amp;#34; removable nylon strap+buckle to hold the lock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 19.00.00.50.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 19.00.00.50.jpg&#34; title=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 19.00.00.50.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Sewing the lock strap on the exterior, using this fabric, is not sturdy. U-locks are heavy, so it sags significantly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 19.00.24.50.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 19.00.24.50.jpg&#34; title=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 19.00.24.50.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Aside from the main pocket, each side has a mini-pocket just for storing a rigid plastic sheet to maintain the structure. I deliberately tucked the flap INSIDE the pocket rather than go over it. It made sense in my head, but it&amp;#39;s clearly the wrong choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 19.01.09.50.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 19.01.09.50.jpg&#34; title=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 19.01.09.50.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Trying to show detail of how the pockets are laid out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 19.01.55.50.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 19.01.55.50.jpg&#34; title=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 19.01.55.50.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Same idea for the yellow bag, but the flap closes over the pocket, and terminates on the outside of the bag rather than the inside. Much sturdier fabric, plus two velcro strips on the ends, instead of one in the middle, mean this bag holds its shape much more than the blue one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Also shows the nylon strap going through the outer layer of the bag (via a &amp;#34;faced opening&amp;#34; made from the ripstop, and through the plastic frame.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This design allowed me to experiment with different insert combinations. There&amp;#39;s plenty of weight to trim here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 19.01.59.50.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 19.01.59.50.jpg&#34; title=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 19.01.59.50.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Outside of the faced opening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 19.02.11.50.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 19.02.11.50.jpg&#34; title=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 19.02.11.50.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Detail of pocket layout&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 21.01.29.50.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 21.01.29.50.jpg&#34; title=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 21.01.29.50.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
detail of pocket flap seam from outside&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 21.03.11.50.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 21.03.11.50.jpg&#34; title=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 21.03.11.50.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
detail of pocket flap seam from inside&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-11 01.58.58.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-11 01.58.58.jpg&#34; title=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-11 01.58.58.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Detail of canvas inside-out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-11 02.00.11.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-11 02.00.11.jpg&#34; title=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-11 02.00.11.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Detail of nylon inside-out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-10&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-10&#34;&gt;
Making the shape template
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-10&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Designing the fabric pattern was the first step. Since the Ortlieb bag includes a plastic insert to give it structure, using that exact shape seemed like the right way to go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/IMG_20190311_141939281.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/IMG_20190311_141939281.jpg&#34; title=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/IMG_20190311_141939281.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I took some rough measurements of the irregular hexagon shape. I could have used these to get pretty close to the right shape. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/IMG_2626-ortlieb-template.25.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/IMG_2626-ortlieb-template.25.jpg&#34; title=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/IMG_2626-ortlieb-template.25.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
However, I have an unreasonable propensity for unnecessary accuracy. I removed the insert, photographed it against a grid, then transformed that photo into vector files for laser cutting. This is great for cutting the pattern from fabric in a repeatable way. Unfortunately I can&amp;#39;t use the laser for the plastic insert itself, so I cut that with a dremel. In the future I might try a bandsaw instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/pattern-illustration.png&#34; alt=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/pattern-illustration.png&#34; title=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/ortlieb-organizer/pattern-illustration.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is a color-coded illustration of the pattern files I used. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Red: plastic insert&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Black: mounting hole cutouts&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blue: &amp;#34;base&amp;#34; fabric pattern&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Green: &amp;#34;tall&amp;#34; fabric pattern, including the flap that covers the mini-pocket for the plastic insert. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I sewed these two fabric pieces together, repeated with another two, then sewed those two pairs together, then turned inside out. Adding velcro, slits, and hems was done at the appropriate steps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The seam margin is .5&amp;#34; in this image, which is what I used for the orange and blue bags. The yellow one is 1&amp;#34;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ortlieb Organizer</title>
      <link>http://alanbernstein.github.io/posts/ortlieb2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://alanbernstein.github.io/posts/ortlieb2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Project log for my organizer insert for Ortlieb Back Roller bike panniers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I commute by bike, including a fair amount of shopping and errands, and I&amp;#39;m kind of obsessed with organization. I use some popular Ortlieb panniers, and I like to think I&amp;#39;ve committed to them as a &amp;#34;platform&amp;#34; for bike storage, long-term. I chose them because they&amp;#39;re spacious, rugged and waterproof, but they&amp;#39;re not made for organization. When fully loaded, I sometimes find myself dumping out all the contents to find something. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, I thought an organizer insert, designed specifically for this bag, and specifically for the items I want to pull out of my bag most frequently, would make a good long-term project. What would that entail, exactly? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At a minimum:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A laptop pocket, closest to the &amp;#34;bike-ward&amp;#34; side of the interior, just because it&amp;#39;s broad and flat&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A place to hang my heavy U-lock&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some kind of structural element to maintain a flat shape, and support the weight of the lock&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Micro-optimizing? Sure, but I just like making things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Some other nice-to-have features:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A quick-release mount to attach to the interior of the Ortlieb bag&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other, smaller, pockets or mounting points for other things, maybe wallet, keys, other bike gear&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, looking to the future, maybe other bags that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compartmentalize and fill out the interior space of the Ortlieb bag&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fold small and flat for storage in case I need the full volume of the bag&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Attach to each other in some clever way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overdesigning is fun; making a solid bag with places for the laptop and lock is my main goal right now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-1&#34;&gt;
Current status
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-2&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-2&#34;&gt;
Iterations
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-2&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-3&#34; class=&#34;outline-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-3&#34;&gt;
v2: canvas, first version that &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; works (2020/05/09)
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-4&#34; class=&#34;outline-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-4&#34;&gt;
v1: ripstop nylon, first minimally viable version (2020/02/25)
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-4&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having a decent idea what the pattern should be, it was now feasible to laser cut it. I cut these out:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nylon: 2x base, 2x tall, .5&amp;#34; seam margin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canvas: 2x base, 2x tall, 1&amp;#34; seam margin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I chose to start with an all-nylon bag. I realized later I might have used canvas for the outside and nylon for the inside. All-nylon was a good choice to start with though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I sewed the nylon pieces together, knowing that it would be easier to sew the other bits on first, but not knowing exactly where to put them. The fabric was thin enough that I could manipulate it enough to sew things on later. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So here&amp;#39;s what I did:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sew base A to tall A to make pocket A&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sew base B to tall B to make pocket B&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sew pocket A to pocket B&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Insert plastic pieces into pockets&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pin velcro to both sides of each pocket (to ensure tight fit)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remove inserts and sew on velcro&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Find locations to attach lock strip, pin webbing in place&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sew on lock strip&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whereas ideally I would have done step three last.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So everything generally works, but the lock is so heavy, it drags the fabric down too much, and it also puts a lot of stress on the webbing-fabric attachment (A single box x stitch). The strip needs more support, and fortunately the plastic insert can do exactly that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-5&#34; class=&#34;outline-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-5&#34;&gt;
v0.2: random scrap fabric, pattern test (2020/01/25)
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-5&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
After the cardboard prototype, I decided I was ready to take on the sewing project. I bought some off-the-shelf fabric that seemed appropriate, and then proceeded to think about how to make the thing for a few months. I spoke with some very helpful people at the Sew and Tell meetup, and finally accepted that I just need to try making it a few times. One of the suggestions was to make that first fabric prototype with cheap scrap fabric, so I tried that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The design was based on the cardboard model, with two broad sides and a thin strip connecting them to give it some volume. I got one big design suggestion at the meetup that allowed me to make progress on this: each side should have a sealable pocket to contain the plastic insert. With that in mind, this first version allowed me to test cutting the pattern, and the sewing process. It turned out that this fabric was awful to work with (very stretchy and very ragged edges), but I definitely learned enough to gain the confidence to work on the next version, with the good fabric.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://alanbernstein.github.io/img/ortlieb-organizer/2020-01-25 21.38.14.50.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/ortlieb-organizer/2020-01-25 21.38.14.50.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/ortlieb-organizer/2020-01-25 21.38.14.50.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I was proud of myself for documenting my learning process with the first bag, but it was not that helpful afterward. I changed the design, and I&amp;#39;ve already internalized the lessons I learned about sewing techniques. Probably most significantly, I abandoned the side strip idea. A laptop fits inside the bag without that added width, and I had a hard time keeping the three pieces of fabric properly aligned. I might want to use a similar approach for a different project later. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Lessons learned:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Began to understand how to think about designing the inside-out object.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When my mental model of the inside-out object fails, I can pin fabric together and turn it inside out to test.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When sewing around a corner, and you need to raise the foot to reposition the work piece, you can rotate it in &lt;strong&gt;either&lt;/strong&gt; direction - it doesn&amp;#39;t have to follow the direction of the seam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I try the thin strip idea again in the future, I will cut it maybe four inches longer than needed, THEN sew it, then trim excess. That will fix half of the alignment problem, but still need to be sure that the two side pieces are lined up properly. It might be easier to use several smaller thin strips, but that would also be uglier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When cutting the pattern, following the curved corners isn&amp;#39;t important: cut a polygonal hull, sew whatever seam you want, then trim. The seam doesn&amp;#39;t even need to be curved, because the bag will take on an organic shape anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The four main parts are attached with three seams, and I put the third one in the wrong place, so the first two were unnecessarily exposed. It occurred to me that I could have just used a single seam, but having multiple seemed like a good idea anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-6&#34; class=&#34;outline-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-6&#34;&gt;
v0.1: cardboard and zip ties, proof-of-concept (2019/02/25)
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-6&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first attempt was a cardboard mockup, held together with zip ties. This worked well enough to prove the concept. It disintegrated after a month or so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://alanbernstein.github.io/img/ortlieb-organizer/IMG_20190224_215759905.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/ortlieb-organizer/IMG_20190224_215759905.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/ortlieb-organizer/IMG_20190224_215759905.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://alanbernstein.github.io/img/ortlieb-organizer/IMG_20190224_225931398.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/ortlieb-organizer/IMG_20190224_225931398.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/ortlieb-organizer/IMG_20190224_225931398.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-7&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-7&#34;&gt;
Sewing process
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-7&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://alanbernstein.github.io/img/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 19.06.12.50.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 19.06.12.50.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 19.06.12.50.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Latest prototype in action. The two main features driving the structural design are the laptop pocket and the U-lock strap.
I&amp;#39;m a sewing beginner, and this is my first design, so I&amp;#39;m learning, making things up as I go, and I probably don&amp;#39;t know a lot of terms that I should. Despite that, I&amp;#39;m very satisfied with this second iteration. It&amp;#39;s truly usable, but I hope to refine it, so I&amp;#39;ll point out a few issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://alanbernstein.github.io/img/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 19.05.29.50.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 19.05.29.50.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 19.05.29.50.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It goes inside this popular Ortlieb pannier. I&amp;#39;m avoiding any permanent modifications to the waterproof exterior. Still figuring out mounting options, but that&amp;#39;s not a major concern, because normally the bag is full enough to keep the organizer in place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://alanbernstein.github.io/img/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 18.57.34.50.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 18.57.34.50.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 18.57.34.50.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
My three prototypes: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Orange: random scrap fabric, to experiment with the basic pattern, not really usable &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blue: random ripstop nylon (specs unknown, but it&amp;#39;s .1mm thick). Includes a sewn-on nylon strap to hold the lock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yellow: random canvas (.6mm thick). Includes a &amp;#34;through-the-frame&amp;#34; removable nylon strap+buckle to hold the lock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://alanbernstein.github.io/img/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 19.00.00.50.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 19.00.00.50.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 19.00.00.50.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Sewing the lock strap on the exterior, using this fabric, is not sturdy. U-locks are heavy, so it sags significantly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://alanbernstein.github.io/img/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 19.00.24.50.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 19.00.24.50.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 19.00.24.50.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Aside from the main pocket, each side has a mini-pocket just for storing a rigid plastic sheet to maintain the structure. I deliberately tucked the flap INSIDE the pocket rather than go over it. It made sense in my head, but it&amp;#39;s clearly the wrong choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://alanbernstein.github.io/img/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 19.01.09.50.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 19.01.09.50.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 19.01.09.50.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Trying to show detail of how the pockets are laid out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://alanbernstein.github.io/img/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 19.01.55.50.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 19.01.55.50.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 19.01.55.50.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Same idea for the yellow bag, but the flap closes over the pocket, and terminates on the outside of the bag rather than the inside. Much sturdier fabric, plus two velcro strips on the ends, instead of one in the middle, mean this bag holds its shape much more than the blue one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Also shows the nylon strap going through the outer layer of the bag (via a &amp;#34;faced opening&amp;#34; made from the ripstop, and through the plastic frame.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This design allowed me to experiment with different insert combinations. There&amp;#39;s plenty of weight to trim here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://alanbernstein.github.io/img/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 19.01.59.50.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 19.01.59.50.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 19.01.59.50.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Outside of the faced opening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://alanbernstein.github.io/img/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 19.02.11.50.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 19.02.11.50.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 19.02.11.50.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Detail of pocket layout&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://alanbernstein.github.io/img/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 21.01.29.50.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 21.01.29.50.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 21.01.29.50.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
detail of pocket flap seam from outside&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://alanbernstein.github.io/img/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 21.03.11.50.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 21.03.11.50.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-09 21.03.11.50.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
detail of pocket flap seam from inside&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://alanbernstein.github.io/img/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-11 01.58.58.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-11 01.58.58.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-11 01.58.58.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Detail of canvas inside-out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://alanbernstein.github.io/img/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-11 02.00.11.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-11 02.00.11.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/ortlieb-organizer/2020-05-11 02.00.11.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Detail of nylon inside-out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-8&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-8&#34;&gt;
Making the shape template
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-8&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Designing the fabric pattern was the first step. Since the Ortlieb bag includes a plastic insert to give it structure, using that exact shape seemed like the right way to go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://alanbernstein.github.io/img/ortlieb-organizer/IMG_20190311_141939281.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/ortlieb-organizer/IMG_20190311_141939281.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/ortlieb-organizer/IMG_20190311_141939281.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I took some rough measurements of the irregular hexagon shape. I could have used these to get pretty close to the right shape. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://alanbernstein.github.io/img/ortlieb-organizer/IMG_2626-ortlieb-template.25.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/ortlieb-organizer/IMG_2626-ortlieb-template.25.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/ortlieb-organizer/IMG_2626-ortlieb-template.25.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
However, I have an unreasonable propensity for unnecessary accuracy. I removed the insert, photographed it against a grid, then transformed that photo into vector files for laser cutting. This is great for cutting the pattern from fabric in a repeatable way. Unfortunately I can&amp;#39;t use the laser for the plastic insert itself, so I cut that with a dremel. In the future I might try a bandsaw instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://alanbernstein.github.io/img/ortlieb-organizer/pattern-illustration.png&#34; alt=&#34;/img/ortlieb-organizer/pattern-illustration.png&#34; title=&#34;/img/ortlieb-organizer/pattern-illustration.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is a color-coded illustration of the pattern files I used. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;span style=&amp;#34;color:red&amp;#34;&amp;gt;Red&amp;lt;/style&amp;gt;: plastic insert&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Black: mounting hole cutouts&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blue: &amp;#34;base&amp;#34; fabric pattern&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Green: &amp;#34;tall&amp;#34; fabric pattern, including the flap that covers the mini-pocket for the plastic insert. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I sewed these two fabric pieces together, repeated with another two, then sewed those two pairs together, then turned inside out. Adding velcro, slits, and hems was done at the appropriate steps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The seam margin is .5&amp;#34; in this image, which is what I used for the orange and blue bags. The yellow one is 1&amp;#34;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tanzania 1: prep</title>
      <link>http://alanbernstein.github.io/posts/tanzania-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://alanbernstein.github.io/posts/tanzania-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I climbed a mountain with &lt;a href=&#34;http://andrearobertson.com/&#34;target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Andrea&lt;/a&gt; and Donna. It took a lot of work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a very long blog post, split into five parts. Check out the &lt;a href=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/trips/kili&#34;target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;slide show&lt;/a&gt; first. Then, if you aren&amp;rsquo;t sure how far you&amp;rsquo;ll get, read parts 3 and 4, then 2, then maybe 1. Part 5 is mostly for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1: prep - &lt;a href=&#34;http://alanbernstein.github.io/posts/tanzania-2&#34;&gt;2: hike&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;a href=&#34;http://alanbernstein.github.io/posts/tanzania-3&#34;&gt;3: summit&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;a href=&#34;http://alanbernstein.github.io/posts/tanzania-4&#34;&gt;4: safari&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;a href=&#34;http://alanbernstein.github.io/posts/tanzania-5&#34;&gt;5: post-mortem&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;a href=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/trips/kili&#34;target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;slide show (upcoming)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/IMG_7422-270.jpg&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Done!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some time in early 2018, Andrea asked me if I wanted to climb &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mount_Kilimanjaro&#34;target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Mount Kilimanjaro&lt;/a&gt;. I hadn&amp;rsquo;t known this was something you could do without significant experience and equipment. It sounded scary and expensive, but after mulling it over for a while, the answer was obvious. I paid my deposit for the seven-day full moon Machame route hike with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kandooadventures.com/climb-kilimanjaro/&#34;target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Kandoo&lt;/a&gt; in March, and spent the next six months researching, training, and shopping.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why did I do it? If you need to ask, I&amp;rsquo;ll never be able to answer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Summiting one of the highest mountains on the planet was a few levels beyond any previous adventures of mine. After booking the trip, I started looking at recommended gear lists, training regimens, and general travel advice for Africa. My todo list to prepare for the trip was huge, but it was easy to get started. Early on, the important thing was to start training as soon as possible. My legs needed practice, everything else could wait a while.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For most people doing the Kilimanjaro climb, altitude sickness, or AMS, is the biggest risk, and it&amp;rsquo;s hard to predict how that will affect you. That means being basically fit is the best thing you can do to prepare, physically. As a bike commuter, my aerobic fitness is fine, so there wasn&amp;rsquo;t much more I could do to prepare. Instead, the most important thing was to get ready to be on my feet for many hours, for days on end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I suppose I&amp;rsquo;d call myself a moderately experienced outdoorsperson. I&amp;rsquo;ve spent plenty of time car camping, and I&amp;rsquo;m always up for a strenuous day hike to climb some modest peak. I had no backpacking experience, but I did do a seven-day self-supported bike touring trip with Kevin a few years ago. Kili is an extended backcountry camping trek full of strenuous, high-altitude hikes, and I was comfortable with each aspect of that on its own, except for the altitude.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m writing all of these posts after the trip, so it will include a handful of retrospective thoughts. &lt;a href=&#34;../tanzania-5&#34;&gt;Part 5&lt;/a&gt; is fully focused on that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;training&#34;&gt;Training&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had been in Austin almost ten years, and somehow just recently learned about &lt;a href=&#34;http://friendsofriverplacetrail.com/&#34;target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;River Place Nature Trail&lt;/a&gt;, the only place to hike near Austin with any appreciable elevation gain. It&amp;rsquo;s about six miles long, with 800 feet of elevation gain, mostly on well-maintained trail stairs. It&amp;rsquo;s a bit of a drive, so not usually too busy, but the narrow trail feels full regardless of how many people are there. This place became our weekend hangout for months, replacing all other outdoor activities. I dragged Lisa and Gizmo along a few times. They were NOT into it. They had more fun at &lt;a href=&#34;https://tpwd.texas.gov/state-parks/enchanted-rock&#34;target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Enchanted Rock&lt;/a&gt;, which is maybe prettier, but much shorter (length and height), much further away, and harder to get into.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ba2f6233-b4c2-4987-9bc5-9ba38253cb42&#34; style=&#34;height: 100%; width: 100%;&#34; class=&#34;plotly-graph-div&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34; src=&#34;http://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img/tanzania/tx-tracks.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Austin is proud of its hills, but that&amp;rsquo;s all we got&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The River Place hikes were great for consistent training. I tried two other things, briefly. I ran three miles on the Hike and Bike trail downtown. By the second time, I was able to finish the run without stopping or walking. I think I could have kept at it and improved, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t enjoy it, and I already get plenty of aerobic exercise on my bike, so I gave it up. I also acquired an altitude training mask, and used it twice before deciding it was useless. After my first Colorado trip, I realized how bad those things are at simulating altitude effects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;21fdd4c7-9e3e-48bf-8fff-1ae47a3c80f0&#34; style=&#34;height: 100%; width: 100%;&#34; class=&#34;plotly-graph-div&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34; src=&#34;http://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img/tanzania/co-tracks.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;More challenging, but there was just too much air to breathe&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I knew hiking that same trail over and over again wasn&amp;rsquo;t enough, so I hoped to make a few short trips to climb some more respectable mountains. There are plenty of options in the US, but I&amp;rsquo;m somehow drawn to Colorado, and I ended up taking two trips there over the summer. I summited Pikes Peak (14114 ft) with Andrea and Donna in July, and Mount Bierstadt (14065 ft) with Cody in August, after a work trip to Denver. Although I&amp;rsquo;ve done serious climbing hikes in the past, these were my first real experience with AMS. Sleeping at about 6000-7000 feet, with just a few days of acclimatisation, I started to feel the effects around 12000 feet. Mostly, mild headache and shortness of breath. The big problem was my inability to pace myself - I would keep exerting myself at normal levels, when my body couldn&amp;rsquo;t handle it. I would stop for ten seconds, then push hard for another 30. I knew this was silly, but I also figured it wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be a problem on Kilimanjaro, since the guides would be setting the pace, instead of me. This turned out to be correct, more or less.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/IMG_6070-pikes.JPG&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Andrea and Donna on the way to Pikes Peak&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second Colorado trip, I was car camping for three days. This was just weeks before the Kilimanjaro trip, so I had most of my gear already. I brought my day pack, and most of the stuff I planned to carry in it, but not much else - somehow, I missed this opportunity to try out all the rest of my new gear. Anyway, I learned one big thing: the day pack I had been using was fine for a couple hours, but after wearing it all day, it was very uncomfortable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/IMG_6451-colorado-camping.JPG&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Colorado car camping con Cody&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To summarize:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find a good place for short hikes near home, and go there a lot.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Summit at least one 14er before the trip.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do a shakedown camp/hike with as much of the gear you plan to bring as possible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;gear&#34;&gt;Gear&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Mount Bierstadt, I met a couple of helpful people. One had done the Kilimanjaro hike several years ago, and gave me two recommendations: get knee-length gaiters, and bring a big daypack. The other guy noticed that I looked like I was stumbling down the path, and decided to keep me company in case the AMS got the better of me. I like to think I was just being lazy and using gravity to assist me in descending faster. In retrospect, I realize it&amp;rsquo;s probably not a good idea to trust your own judgment in that sort of situation. Anyway, that guy recommended &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.wildernessx.com/&#34;target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Wilderness Exchange&lt;/a&gt; in Denver, so I stopped there on my way to the airport, and replaced my cheap craigslist daypack (a $45 like-new Osprey Mira 26) with a $100 lightly-used Osprey Mutant 38. Incidentally, that&amp;rsquo;s my new favorite store. The consignment and manufacturer sample sections make it almost a cross between REI and Goodwill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, back to the beginning. I read through a handful of gear recommendation lists, and found at least one person&amp;rsquo;s actual packing list, and I compiled all of those into a series of lists for myself: definitely buy, maybe buy, already have. The basics are critical: good everyday hiking clothes, packable cold-weather gear, duffel bag and day pack, boots. About three years ago, I learned about the magic of Merino wool. I started buying Merino stuff for biking - 2X Icebreaker t-shirts and 5 pairs of ultralight Smartwool socks - most of which I brought to Kilimanjaro. Living in Texas, I don&amp;rsquo;t have much use for cold-weather clothes, so this was an excuse to acquire some. The majority of new apparel I bought totaled about $300.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About three months before the trip, the sole of one of my hiking boots started coming loose. I was annoyed at the time, but I&amp;rsquo;m so glad it didn&amp;rsquo;t happen any later - plenty of time to find new boots and wear them in. I briefly debated trying to use the dying boots on the trip, which would have been an awful idea. I saw 5-10 lost soles over the course of the hike, and if that had happened to me, it would have been worse than anything else that did. So, I donated my seven-year-old boots to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/ProjectShoehorn/?rc=p&#34;target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Project Shoehorn&lt;/a&gt;, and got some new mid-range waterproof Oboz boots. I considered getting higher-end Vasque or Salomon boots. Even though I expect to use them plenty, I didn&amp;rsquo;t see the point. Maybe next time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A waterproof duffelbag is suggested, so I got both the Patagonia 60L and 90L, hoping to make the smaller one work. I ended up using the 90L and returning the 60L, but with what I know now, I&amp;rsquo;m sure I could have managed with the 60L (with my 38L daypack stuffed full for the flights).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generally speaking, I try to avoid buying new things when possible, preferring hand-me-downs, Craigslist, Goodwill, etc. This kind of trip necessitates some specific items, that fit well, so I mostly gave up on being able to do that. Shortly before the trip, REI announced their new online used gear store, so I was happy to give that a chance. I looked through every available item, and found two things perfect for the trip - a cold-weather sleeping bag, and a decent-sized, waterproof mountaineering day pack. I ordered them, and they just never showed up! This was pretty annoying, and I&amp;rsquo;m pretty unlikely to use that shop again in the future. Oh well. I already had a three-season sleeping bag, which wasn&amp;rsquo;t warm enough, so I got a liner, which doesn&amp;rsquo;t do much. I ended up renting one of Kandoo&amp;rsquo;s sleeping bags, a Mountain Hardwear Lamina -30. This thing was huge and super warm, some nights I didn&amp;rsquo;t even zip it up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We used Kandoo&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Mountain-Hardwear-Trango-Tent-Orange/dp/B00IG9JOW2&#34;target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Mountain Hardwear Trango 3&lt;/a&gt; tents. These were pretty nice. I&amp;rsquo;m glad we didn&amp;rsquo;t have to set them up and take them down ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s all the new stuff I bought:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;amount&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;item&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;82.27&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;smartwool pants base layer&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;15.36&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;darn tough hiking socks&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8.99&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;microfiber towel&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;189.44&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;oboz hiking boots&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9.90&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;uniqlo heattech undershirt&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;14.90&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;uniqlo rain pants&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;29.90&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;uniqlo down jacket&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;45.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;osprey mira day pack&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;21.60&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;REI stuff sacks&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;75.72&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;peak design capture clip&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;19.22&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;cheap wool socks&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;21.53&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;patagonia shirt&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;107.65&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;osprey mutant 38 pack&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5.67&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;heavy thread (repair kit)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;19.99&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;trekking poles&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;22.99&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;down hood&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;161.29&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;patagonia duffel 90L&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6.50&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;rite in the rain notebook&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;48.71&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;smartwool boxers&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;250.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;70-300 lens&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10.88&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;bandanas&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11.19&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;inflatable pillow&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;24.19&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;black diamond headlamp&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;37.99&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;gorillapod&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12.93&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.5L nalgene&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;31.39&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;buff&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9.11&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;bottle sling&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;29.99&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;anker 10Ah battery&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;45.47&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;osprey hydration pack&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;75.72&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;burton mittens&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;ndash;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;-&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;1445.49&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;total&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I bought a lot of it just before the trip, after deliberating on whether I needed it, and exhausting other options besides purchasing new. Most of this is self-explanatory: clothes, bags, shoes, mittens, poles, head lamp. The camera gear makes sense if you&amp;rsquo;re a photographer. That stuff makes up almost $1300 of the total, leaving just a few odds and ends. Most of that is also obvious, the only exception is the nalgene and the bottle sling - highly recommended for summit night because bladder hoses can freeze. The idea is to put the nalgene in the sling upside down, so the water freezes from the bottom. I used the nalgene bottle plenty, and I&amp;rsquo;m glad I brought it, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t use it at all on summit night. I also bought and returned over $600 worth of stuff that didn&amp;rsquo;t make the cut.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also borrowed an inflatable sit pad, plus a bunch of stuff sacks and carabiners, from Patsy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/IMG_6580-packing-categorized.JPG&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;All my stuff, minus my ebook reader. Analysis in &lt;a href=&#34;../tanzania-5&#34;&gt;part 5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;photography&#34;&gt;Photography&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/2018-10-03-07.02.55-packing-camera.jpg&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Photography gear&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Half of it I already had - the T6i, Tamron 10-24 f/3.5-4.5, Canon 50 f/1.8, and miscellaneous accessories - and I also got a few new toys. First, a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.peakdesign.com/products/capture&#34;target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;capture clip&lt;/a&gt;, at the recommendation of a friend. Kind of pricey, but I&amp;rsquo;m glad I got it. Second, my first telephoto lens, a Canon 70-300 IS. If a safari isn&amp;rsquo;t a good enough excuse to get a telephoto, then what is? It&amp;rsquo;s a low/midrange lens, nothing fancy, but I still got some great shots with it. Finally, a Gorillapod, which I figured I would only use for night photos. I was right, and it was totally worth it. Without it, I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t have gotten this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/IMG_7178-ghost.JPG&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m a ghost&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also bought a set of knockoff batteries, to ensure my camera would last until summit night. I was hesitant to use those, for fear of hurting my camera&amp;rsquo;s precious feelings, but my Canon battery lasted the entire hike anyway. Plus, both my mind and my fingers were unusable at that point, so I gave up on photos at the summit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;packing&#34;&gt;Packing&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We put some thought into how we would pack for the different phases of the trip. Donna packed a small bag of clothes for each hike day, which I thought was overkill, and unlikely to work for me. Instead, I focused on what to put in each of my main bags for the flight, and for the hike. The safari was an afterthought, since I didn&amp;rsquo;t know anything about it anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I actually used five distinct bags over the course of the trip: duffel, daypack, passport pouch, light drawstring bag, and a folding reusable shopping bag (to leave stuff behind at the hotel while hiking).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The passport pouch held my passport, yellow card, wallet, giant wad of 10000 shilling notes (basically $5 bills, which is what the ATMs dispense, I guess), and a small knife, flashlight, and pencil, and spare SD cards for my camera. I kept this around my shoulder or in my daypack most of the time, but definitely didn&amp;rsquo;t have it on my person all the time during the hike, like I should have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the flights, the recommendation is to carry the hiking essentials in your carry-on, so I packed my most expensive, hard-to-replace clothes and gear in my daypack (plus camera and lenses), and stuffed everything else in my duffel. I used the drawstring bag for minimal flight essentials (headphones, sleep mask, book, snacks, jacket), which worked well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the hike, my daypack would carry water, rain gear, one warmth layer if I wasn&amp;rsquo;t wearing it, trekking poles, snacks and toiletries, first aid kit and repair kit, and my camera and lenses. Most everything else stayed in the duffel, including all the other camera stuff. I wore hiking pants with some big pockets, which usually ended up full of snacks, toiletries, and lenses, lightening the weight in my daypack a bit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I unintentionally ended up with a nice rainbow assortment of stuff sacks of various sizes. This was super convenient for organization, especially when trying to find something buried deep in a dark bag. Need underwear or socks? Find the yellow bag, pull it out, get what you need, toss it back in. I&amp;rsquo;ll continue using that system in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- TODO: packing party pic --&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;miscellaneous&#34;&gt;Miscellaneous&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My previous experience with bike touring made me worry about my knees. I often make smoothies for breakfast, and I use whey protein powder. A few months before the trip, I switched to collagen, in the hopes that it would strengthen my joints. I don&amp;rsquo;t know if there&amp;rsquo;s any science to suggest this would work, and I had no experimental control to evaluate the difference. That said, my knees (and other joints) had absolutely no trouble on the trip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some people recommend a level of mental preparation that I felt was unnecessary. One suggestion is a mantra. I didn&amp;rsquo;t have one, but if I had, it would have been &amp;ldquo;time is an illusion&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;documents-etc&#34;&gt;Documents, etc&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I brought the obvious stuff: passport, flight info, insurance info, driver&amp;rsquo;s license, credit card, debit card. Also, a few pages of info from Kandoo, and prescription info sheets. Other than that, and a small notebook, I tried to minimize paper. Instead I loaded a bunch of info onto my phone. Manuals, all the documents from Kandoo and my insurance, maps of the mountain, a handful of wikipedia page PDFs (like &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mount_Kilimanjaro&#34;target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt;, which I read in full, one sleepless night), GPS tracks from my own hikes, and from others&#39; Kili experiences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/2018-10-07-09.06.10-notebook.jpg&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Warning: water-proof notebooks are NOT banana-proof&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mostly, I tried to condense all important information into a few pages of this little waterproof notebook that I got for the trip. Emergency contacts, flight info, travel reference info, notes on meds and AMS, and info about the various climates of the hike. After that, I dedicated one page to each day of the trip, with major itinerary points, todo items, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mountain-forecast.com/peaks/Mount-Kilimanjaro/forecasts/5963&#34;target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;weather forecasts&lt;/a&gt;, and a summary of the hike, including a rough elevation profile. Of course it was also nice to keep it accessible for taking notes. Overkill maybe; I didn&amp;rsquo;t need any of this aside from the basic trip details and emergency info, but I&amp;rsquo;m glad I had it. I just like knowing what&amp;rsquo;s going on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I planned to bring enough American cash to cover all expenses, plus one credit card for emergencies. Andrea changed my mind (&amp;ldquo;cash isn&amp;rsquo;t protected from fraud&amp;rdquo;), and Donna brought cash, and I think Donna did it right. Stopping at an ATM was a hassle and a risk, and they dispensed 10000 shilling notes, which are worth about $5. You want to carry cash on your body, so it should be as value-dense as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some person or website recommended getting your visa early; I was under the impression this step was required. It saved a few minutes on arrival, but it cost another $30 for shipping, and it required sending my passport in the mail, which was disconcerting. I won&amp;rsquo;t bother in the future unless it&amp;rsquo;s strictly required.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;consumables&#34;&gt;Consumables&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/2018-09-15-10.46.49-packing-snacks.jpg&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Unsuspecting prey&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m a hungry kind of guy, so when the packing lists included &amp;ldquo;Personal snacks&amp;rdquo;, but my contact at Kandoo said it wasn&amp;rsquo;t necessary, I erred on the side of caution. I packed about 30 snack bars, maybe 5000 calories worth, plus a pound of almonds, some candied ginger, and some jelly bellys. It felt like overkill, but I brought it all anyway. Also, a fresh, full-sized bottle of the best hot sauce, chipotle tabasco.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/2018-09-28-06.50.45-tabasco.jpg&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;O ye, of little faith&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For toiletries, I just brought the usual, plus extra sunscreen and bug spray, two rolls of toilet paper, three packs of wet wipes, and three ounces of hand sanitizer. I&amp;rsquo;ve almost never used wet wipes or hand sanitizer before, but I figured this was a good time to start.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, a first aid kit and a repair kit. I left out some gauze and medical tape, and instead brought an ace bandage and two cold compresses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/IMG_6584-packing-med.JPG&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mostly self-explanatory&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/IMG_6586-packing-repair.JPG&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Clips, straps, strips, snaps&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had guides who could probably have solved any real problems we had on the hike, so maybe not necessary. I carry stuff like this around on a normal day, so I wasn&amp;rsquo;t going to Africa without it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;medical&#34;&gt;Medical&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I got most of the recommended immunizations, yellow fever, hepatitis B, tetanus, and typhoid, with no trouble. Rabies is recommended as well, but when I asked my travel nurse about it in an email, she didn&amp;rsquo;t even respond, so I didn&amp;rsquo;t worry about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With less than two weeks left before the trip, I spotted a loose pet dog wandering around outside my house, and I went out to try to help him get home. He bit me, making the tiniest puncture wound, that almost certainly carried no risk. Since he escaped and was not found by animal control, when I went to a doctor they had no choice but to start me on full post-exposure rabies immunization. If you&amp;rsquo;re unfamiliar, that means four immediate shots of immunoglobulin, spread out on the same side of my body as the bite, plus four more of the vaccine, on the other side of my body. Those vaccine shots are supposed to be given on days 0, 3, 7 and 14 after the bite, but on day 14, I would be gone. A few days of mild panic ensued, during which I failed to find any consistent information on how to adjust the schedule. The doctor giving the shots had no idea, I called other doctors and the manufacturer, checked CDC and WHO recommendations, and then gave up on finding an answer. Some internet person told me I should cancel the trip, but I decided to accept the risk of getting rabies from a pet husky in Texas, rather than forfeit thousands of dollars for the trip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I got three prescriptions. Diamox for AMS, and atovaquone for malaria. With atovaquone, you start taking it two days before entering a risk area, and then continue for seven days after leaving. My travel nurse said only the safari portion of the trip counted as risk days, and I would be fine for the day and a half before the hike, as long as I stayed indoors at night. Although I may not have been at any real risk of contracting malaria, I definitely dealt with mosquitoes in my hotel room before the hike. After that happened, I decided to ask for enough to cover a full trip, if I ever need it in the future. On the other hand, Tommy, the traveling doctor from my group, says he never takes malaria prophylaxis. The last one was ciprofloxacin, an antibiotic for severe traveller&amp;rsquo;s diarrhea. The side effects of this stuff include &amp;ldquo;tendon rupture&amp;rdquo;, usually the Achilles tendon. Probably almost no chance it would happen to me, but I was pretty sure I&amp;rsquo;d rather suffer diarrhea than risk that anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, a handful of over-the-counter meds: Immodium AD, which I didn&amp;rsquo;t use, but shared with others. Pepto Bismol, which I started eating like candy after my stomach had one rough day. Ibuprofen, which I was afraid to take, for fear of masking important pain signals. I did take a couple after the summit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;playlist&#34;&gt;Playlist&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many people prepare a summit playlist, &amp;ldquo;Ain&amp;rsquo;t no mountain high enough&amp;rdquo;, etc. I needed only &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FTQbiNvZqaY&#34;target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;one song&lt;/a&gt;. A few other good tracks came to me during the hike though, so I&amp;rsquo;ll record for posterity:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mzDVaKRApcg&#34;target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Higher and higher&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4yk7M7aneCA&#34;target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Green typewriters 10&lt;/a&gt;, a sleepy track from my favorite band, because of one line: &amp;ldquo;When you&amp;rsquo;re ready to come back down, I&amp;rsquo;ll be waiting&amp;rdquo;. Probably about drugs, but really, being that far up a mountain is its own high, so not inappropriate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anything from The Lion King. I hadn&amp;rsquo;t realized how appropriate this would have been, as the movie is arguably &amp;ldquo;set&amp;rdquo; in Tanzania or maybe Kenya, Kili makes a brief appearance, and &amp;ldquo;Hakuna Matata&amp;rdquo; is actually a common Swahili phrase. At least, it is in the tourist experience.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Head, shoulders knees and toes. Yes the kids song. To remind you of everything that hurts. AMS headache, heavy pack on your shoulders, knees do all the climbing, toes compressed in your boots and blistering.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;expenses&#34;&gt;Expenses&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The climb itself cost $2695. Depending on how you count it, the trip cost me about $8000 total. That includes &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt; - the three-day safari plus lodging, flights, BOTH Colorado trips, and all the gear I bought and will continue using (including $300+ of photography stuff).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously, things like gear and flights will vary quite a bit from person to person. Here&amp;rsquo;s my breakdown:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;amount&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;thing&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2695.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;climb&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1445.49&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;gear&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1156.51&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;africa flights&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;954.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;safari&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;792.85&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;pikes peak trip&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;500.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;incidentals (tips, drinks, food, souvenirs)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;105.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;vaccinations&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;135.81&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;visa application (30.81 shipping)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;100&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;denver trip (work covered flights, cheap camping)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;78.61&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;travel insurance&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;50.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;sleeping bag rental&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;20.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;prescriptions&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;120.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;misc consumables&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;ndash;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;8153.27&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;total&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If that seems like a lot&amp;hellip; it is. Even without the cost of the Colorado trips and the gear, this was the most expensive thing I&amp;rsquo;ve ever done, aside from those big life milestones. I think it cost more than my wedding.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tanzania 2: Hike</title>
      <link>http://alanbernstein.github.io/posts/tanzania-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://alanbernstein.github.io/posts/tanzania-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I climbed a mountain with &lt;a href=&#34;http://andrearobertson.com/&#34;target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Andrea&lt;/a&gt; and Donna. We hiked five days to get to base camp.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a very long blog post, split into five parts. If you aren&amp;rsquo;t sure how far you&amp;rsquo;ll get, read parts 3 and 4, then 2, then maybe 1. Part 5 is mostly for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../tanzania-1&#34;&gt;1: prep&lt;/a&gt; - 2: hike - &lt;a href=&#34;../tanzania-3&#34;&gt;3: summit&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;a href=&#34;../tanzania-4&#34;&gt;4: safari&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;a href=&#34;../tanzania-5&#34;&gt;5: post-mortem&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;a href=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/trips/kili&#34;target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;slide show (upcoming)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Normally I like to keep a journal while traveling, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t do a great job of it on this trip. I only brought my small notebook of reference info with me, which didn&amp;rsquo;t have space for real journaling. Instead, I used my phone to track some technical info over the course of the hike, so I ended up with something more like a lab notebook. I hope this will be helpful for me when preparing for future backpacking trips. To my future self, or anyone trying to use this as practical advice: remember this hike was in late September in Africa, spanning a wide range of climates and temperatures, eating foreign food and having most of my stuff carried by porters. Maybe not the most relevant for other hikes, but still some good info.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did record things that stood out on some days, but I&amp;rsquo;m mostly counting on the 2365 photos and videos I took to help remember all the little things. I&amp;rsquo;m writing this as soon as possible after getting home, but I&amp;rsquo;m sure I&amp;rsquo;ve already lost some of the memories =(&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That makes this a good opportunity to get started on a project I&amp;rsquo;ve been thinking about for a while. I want a web app that generates a travel journal page, based on a set of photos, journal notes, and GPS tracks. This is a work in progress, but check it out &lt;a href=&#34;alanbernstein.net/trips/kili&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;arrival&#34;&gt;Arrival&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We flew on KLM, Houston-Amsterdam-Kilimanjaro (yeah, there&amp;rsquo;s an airport for the mountain, JRO). We live in Austin, so we left at 8am for our 3pm flight. Donna&amp;rsquo;s daughter Laura Anne gave us a ride - this trip was so big, it consumed two vacation days of a person who didn&amp;rsquo;t even go with us. At IAH, there were no lines, but the checkin counter wasn&amp;rsquo;t open until 11:30 (how quaint), so we had half an hour to kill. When Andrea tried to check a bag, she was told her carry-on was too heavy. Funny, because they didn&amp;rsquo;t even weigh mine, and Andrea&amp;rsquo;s solution was to move some stuff to her checked bag&amp;hellip; just redistributing weight on the airplane.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, we made it onto the plane, and we split up so Andrea and Donna could enjoy their fancy upgraded seats with four extra inches of leg room. Mine was fine, as cheap plane seats go. The entertainment system was nice, I watched a bunch of movies. Also, one episode of new Macgyver. Did you know there was a new Macgyver? It&amp;rsquo;s bad. They served us two meals on each flight, and sometimes an ice cream cone too. Nice folks. I found the in-flight chatroom system, and invited Andrea to a room. We sent a single message each, without knowing what the other was sending&amp;hellip; and it was the same message.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/2018-09-19-03.35.24-hillary.jpg&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lisa said &amp;ldquo;you guys are weird&amp;rdquo; when she saw this&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schipol, the Amsterdam airport, is neat. High end stores, if that&amp;rsquo;s your thing. They have a mini art museum, sadly closed for renovations, and a loose collection of interactive science exhibits. Everything was on time, so we had a couple hours to kill during the layover. We stretched our legs, and made some last minute stops at a pharmacy and a snack shop. Kandoo suggests bringing a &amp;ldquo;favorite snack&amp;rdquo; to encourage yourself to eat when AMS kills your appetite, and I finally figured out that a Ghirardelli chocolate caramel bar was the answer to that. By far, the best part of the layover was seeing a security guard eat shit while speeding around on his segway (he was ok).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We deboarded at JRO on the tarmac, and I realized how big that plane was. It&amp;rsquo;s hard to appreciate from the inside, you don&amp;rsquo;t notice that the engines are twice as tall as a person. Navigating JRO on the way in was no problem, we found our driver holding up a Kandoo sign, met a few of our group, and drove to our hotel. Our flight had arrived at 9pm, so we didn&amp;rsquo;t have a chance to see much. When we reached our hotel, the driver helped unload, then stood next to Andrea and whispered something. Nobody understood, and he had to repeat himself three times before somebody figured out he was asking for tips. We knew there&amp;rsquo;d be plenty of tipping, so this shy request confused us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;final-prep&#34;&gt;Final prep&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After one night and a quick breakfast buffet at Park View Hotel, we moved on to Stella Maris, the proper staging ground for the hike. The rest of our group was there (or would be), along with another Kandoo group on the same schedule. On the way, we made a few stops in town. Andrea and I needed some cash, so we stopped at some corner with an ATM. Andrea withdrew the maximum amount, and the machine said it was dispensed, but that was a lie. An armed guard standing outside the attached bank saw us panicking and tried to help. He, or maybe our driver, said it was a network connectivity problem. Not reassuring! We all went into the bank to try to sort it out, and we had to pass through a buffered security door, one at a time. They were no help. I went to another ATM across the street, and got some cash with no trouble. Andrea got some cash one way or another, and the lying robot did the right thing, eventually.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had mentioned needing to buy a few things, so of course our next stop was the driver&amp;rsquo;s favorite souvenir shop. I did want a postcard for my niblings, so no big deal. They also had jewelry made from bits of aluminum soda cans. Scrappy. Next up: a pharmacy, to find some first aid things that I foolishly left at home. This was an odd experience because everything in the store was purchased by asking the clerk to go get it. Makes sense for drugs, but it was like this even for bandaids. It was only a problem because I was trying to find something specific, not knowing the local brands or terms. So I had this silly back-and-forth with the clerk, trying to cross the language barrier to figure out what they had that would work for me. Mostly, I was trying to deal with this weird rash on my foot (mysterious allergic reaction, I guess), and I needed some large bandages to keep it clean. The only option was this ridiculous roll of gauze, the thinnest fabric imaginable. Better than nothing, so I got it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We gave up on getting a sim card, and my brilliant plan to buy a Gatorade to use as a pee bottle failed because they have no Gatorade there. Instead, I bought some dumb plastic bottle in the hotel for $20, didn&amp;rsquo;t use it once, then donated it to the porters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- TODO: seeing stuff in tanzania for the first time --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/IMG_6624-andrea-donna-packing.JPG&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Just expect all of your stuff to be a big mess, all the time&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We spent the rest of the day repacking, eating, meeting our group, and getting our last hits of internet for the next week. I tried the one interesting drink in the hotel&amp;rsquo;s fridge, a bitter lemon soda called Krest. It tasted how you&amp;rsquo;d expect. Andrea mentioned that she was concerned about a bad reaction to diamox, because of a sulfa allergy. Trying to be helpful, I found some random web forum post saying it&amp;rsquo;s a strong contraindication, so Andrea decided to skip the diamox. That might have been partly responsible for her having a rough time in general, and day 3 in particular, like most of the group. She made it to Stella Point anyway, so I only feel a little bit bad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last thing left on my hike prep todo list was to get an offline topographical map on my phone, so I spent a few minutes on Andrea&amp;rsquo;s laptop trying to figure that out. The USGS is amazing, but not so useful in places like Tanzania. There seemed to be two options: pay $100 for a lifetime subscription to Alltrails, or create my own georeferenced PDF map files, to use in Avenza. I don&amp;rsquo;t like the Alltrails app, and hobbyist georeferencing seems to depend on a precarious stack of open source tools, so neither of these worked out. Thanks, Andrea, for letting me install a bunch of random crap on your laptop. I like having good maps while hiking; Andrea and Donna worked on preparing a different resource at the last minute: inspirational quote flashcards. Donna couldn&amp;rsquo;t find the set she brought, so we came together as a team to figure out how to print some replacements at the hotel. I took one more shower, doing my best to avoid the mosquitoes that my travel nurse told me wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be a problem indoors, then said my last goodbye to Lisa, and went to bed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/2018-09-20-16.35.46-briefing.jpg&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The situation room&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next morning, we had our first briefing with our lead guide, Richard. I think most of us knew what to expect, so we listened for a few minutes, did our first health check (Joanne, after seeing my resting heart rate: &amp;ldquo;Cool as a cucumber, aren&amp;rsquo;t you? We&amp;rsquo;ll see what the mountain has to say about that&amp;rdquo;), and talked about gear rental. Kandoo provides the tents and some basic foam sleeping mats, and they also rent trekking poles and serious cold-weather sleeping bags. I needed a bag, so I got one, but at this point I was worried about my duffel weight and volume, and the quality of the sleeping mat. I ended up bringing my own mat as well. Their sleeping bags are huge, like a five-gallon propane tank, and we were told they were 4kg, a big chunk of our 15kg duffel limit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next we played the fun game of final packing, with a strict weight limit. The hotel had a room where we could leave stuff behind, and we all made use of that, but it was still a challenge. My huge daypack was sort of an advantage, though I was worried about the weight. I brought way more stuff than I needed, but as my first real backpacking trip, I have no regrets. I was worried I&amp;rsquo;d have to give something up, when I realized the 1.5L nalgene bottle in my duffel bag was still full of water&amp;hellip; so that was an easy fix.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought it was clever to adopt the shorthand used by Kandoo on their itinerary form: the seven days of the Machame route hike are M1-M7, and the safari days are S1-S3. I used these in my notes, and forgot what day of the week it was, as soon as I got on the plane. Of course, others preferred using weekdays to talk about the hike. Between that, accents, and my FREEDOM UNITS, I had some sort of language barrier with almost everyone on the hike.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;people&#34;&gt;People&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This seems like a good place to introduce everyone, my family for the following seven days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/IMG_6607-austin-crew.JPG&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Donna, Andrea, and me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/hikers.jpg&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other six hikers in our group: Tommy, KJ, Natalie, Chen, Joanne, and Joanne.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/staff.jpg&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our lead guide Richard, and guides Kisima, Tila, and Disimus. Bottom left is Mr. Delicious, our chef/porter. Bottom right is the full staff including 26 porters. Of those, one was a server, one a dust-brusher, and one an acting guide for summit night. I didn&amp;rsquo;t speak to them as much as the guides; I think they generally don&amp;rsquo;t speak English as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-hike&#34;&gt;The hike&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We did the seven-day Machame route (AKA the whiskey route, because it&amp;rsquo;s harder than the Marangu route, AKA the coca cola route, which was popular and touristy). The mountain is well-traveled, there is a full circuit trail, and maybe seven gates, so lots of ways to go. Machame seems to be the most popular these days, but I just did it because I trusted Andrea and Donna to make the plans. The choice of route dictates which campsites you can stay at, and therefore the duration of the hike, more or less.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We rode the bus for an hour, passing through town, and then some forest villages at the base of the mountain, before arriving at our gate. Kilimanjaro is a free-standing mountain, which means the climate zones are rings around the summit. Some combination of elevation, snowmelt, and volcanic soil (maybe) supports agriculture, which was obvious on the way up to the gate. It looked like we were driving through a hilly farming village, banana trees right next to storefronts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- kili-track-gmaps-wide.png --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;video autoplay muted loop width=700px src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/kili-flyover-1.webm&#34;&gt;&lt;/video&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Our hike route. The rainforest ring zone is clearly visible in satellite photos&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the bus arrived, we sat around for an hour or so, waiting for permits, checking our packs, eating the boxed lunch we were given, despite having eaten breakfast just a few hours previously. We filled out the first of our registration forms; the entrance gate and every camp had to record our info, including name, nationality and occupation. Filling out my own info, I caught a glimpse of some of the others&#39; in my group. We hung out in a big pavilion by the gate, along with three or four other groups. Finally, after months of preparation, and hours of travel, we were ready to start, so we did. If the beginning of the trek felt anticlimactic, the summit climb made up for it, many times over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, we walked, a lot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll just be honest - the hiking part was easy. Being fit helps, I&amp;rsquo;m sure. Knowing what to expect from high altitude was great. All the training I did was worth it. That said, the days of the trek were [../tough-mudder#obstacles](no challenge). Summit night, however, was the most physically taxing activity I have ever experienced. We&amp;rsquo;ll get to that soon enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was early on the first day that I noticed Joanne carrying an e-cigarette. She was the only one of the nine hikers that didn&amp;rsquo;t make it to at least Stella Point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;034d8252-7cd7-4667-a4d0-05d41849d087&#34; style=&#34;height: 100%; width: 100%;&#34; class=&#34;plotly-graph-div&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34; src=&#34;http://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img/tanzania/kili-tracks.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;My daily elevation profiles&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every day had its own challenges, new terrain, a different feel. In the end, most of it is just putting one foot in front of the other, for as many hours as it takes. I&amp;rsquo;m not even sure what I could have written down at the time, to capture the feeling of each day. Mostly, I remember talking with the group and the guides, thinking about how far we had left to go, looking ahead to the daunting trail visible in front of us, and turning around once in a while to appreciate the view. I hoped I could depend on some photos to remind myself of each day&amp;rsquo;s terrain, and I wrote down a few things that stood out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Day 1 was five or six hours of hiking, a good warmup. Not too strenuous, not too high, but a good chance to remind our legs that they had some work to do. The first few hours, everything was still sinking in. We&amp;rsquo;re really on the mountain, past the point of no return. Early on, we spotted some wildlife and stopped to smell some flowers. We passed a bathroom, which was a pair of squat toilets in stalls. A few us of tried it, and that was the last time we bothered with a &amp;ldquo;tourist toilet&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We stopped at a small clearing to eat lunch. This is what the boxed lunches were for - we were supposed to pack them. If I had known that at the beginning of the day, I might have had room for it in my pack. We finished, got back on the trail, and saw another group eating lunch, with a full portable set of table and chairs. I thought we were looking at a group with a luxury hiking package, but the truth is, our porters were carrying all the same gear for us, they just didn&amp;rsquo;t set it up for lunch that day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/IMG_6677-porter-carry.JPG&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Superhuman&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a lot about the porters&#39; responsibilities that I didn&amp;rsquo;t quite grasp, before seeing them do it all on the mountain. Throughout the hike, we&amp;rsquo;d be passed by porters carrying an absurd amount of gear. Most commonly, they would have one backpack, 50-60 liters or so, plus another, bigger load, balanced on top of their heads, or carried on top of their backpack and shoulders. And their job doesn&amp;rsquo;t end with carrying it. On a normal day, they would wait for us to leave camp, take everything down, carry it all to the next camp &lt;em&gt;faster&lt;/em&gt; than we could get there with our light loads, then set it all up before we arrived. Maybe they&amp;rsquo;d have dinner cooking already. Oh, and many of them wore whatever clothes and shoes they could manage; no specialty hiking gear, no fancy fabrics. I noticed one porter wearing old tennis shoes, with one sole half detached and flapping around. In the rain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two other things I didn&amp;rsquo;t appreciate until I saw them myself: the amount of people, and the amount of trash. There was never a time when we were really alone on the trail, not as individuals, nor as a group. I think I heard that something like 15000 tourists climb the mountain per year. Considering seasonality, there might have been 100 hikers in our cohort, which means maybe 10 groups of 40 people each. All of those people hiking the same route, staying at the same camps, leaving at the same time every morning. Plus other groups on routes that overlapped ours. For long stretches of the day, I was just one person in a long chain of hikers and porters; sometimes I couldn&amp;rsquo;t even see the beginning or the end. Even after separating a bit, we would frequently pass other groups, or be passed by one or two porters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Porters were like the cars to the pedestrian hikers. On the first day, we put some effort into figuring out the trail etiquette. &amp;ldquo;Porters on your left!&amp;rdquo; Andrea would say. Because nobody seemed to be following the &amp;ldquo;pass on the left&amp;rdquo; standard, I started to think the &amp;ldquo;on your left&amp;rdquo; part wasn&amp;rsquo;t helpful, so I&amp;rsquo;d just say &amp;ldquo;three porters behind!&amp;rdquo;. Eventually, I realized the porters often don&amp;rsquo;t care to wait for the hikers to figure out they&amp;rsquo;re being passed, so they just take whatever route they can find that gets them past the slowpokes. If it worked for them, it was fine for me. The only issue was the occasional porter carrying the long, spiky poles for the big tents, which stick out dangerously far, at face level, and almost snagged people a few times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, there&amp;rsquo;s the trash. Kandoo was very clear about their leave-no-trace philosophy, which is a great thing to say, but clearly not followed broadly enough. I read that human waste became a big problem, prompting better toilet solutions. Still, toilets are only available at camp, so there is plenty of waste and toilet paper strewn about the trail. That stuff is bad enough, but there is even more litter. Sometimes there would be long stretches where I couldn&amp;rsquo;t go one minute without seeing a bit of trash. I asked a guide about this, and he guessed that porters might be responsible. I don&amp;rsquo;t know what&amp;rsquo;s a more depressing thought, the litter being from tourists, or from the locals who take their livelihood from the mountain. At home, I recently started carrying a trash bag when I hike to collect litter, but it wasn&amp;rsquo;t feasible on the mountain. On day 3, I realized that one of our guides carried a small trash bag, so I started collecting some. When Kisima carried it, he&amp;rsquo;d say &amp;ldquo;Thank you for cleaning up my office!&amp;rdquo; when I put some in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the introductions were done, so this was our first opportunity to temporarily pair off and start getting to know the others in our group. It was around this time that I remembered seeing Tommy&amp;rsquo;s occupation on a registration form - physician - and asked him about it. I think Donna said &amp;ldquo;oh, he&amp;rsquo;ll have some questions for you then&amp;rdquo;. I said no, I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to burden him on his vacation, but he brushed that off. I learned that KJ, the group&amp;rsquo;s other photographer, is from India and living in the UK. Natalie was in Tanzania for the hike, then staying for three months afterward to teach English and health at a girls&#39; school. The three British girls were from Liverpool. At some point football came up, so the conversation went in one of my ears and out the other, regardless of which kind of football it was.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/IMG_6847-camp.JPG&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Our tents are the group of orange+white and black ones. This is day 2.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We arrived at Machame camp at 4:30pm, after about five hours of hiking. This camp is a collection of small clearings in the woods. I got the impression that porters are free to choose the first spot they find that works for them. Our group&amp;rsquo;s camp was seven three-person tents for the hikers and guides, a toilet tent, a big mess tent, and one (or two?) more big tent for the porters and for cooking. Also, usually, all our bags piled up on a tarp on the ground. We slept two people to a tent, with enough extra space for all our stuff, so we could repack and get dressed in the tent. The mess tent was a new experience to me. This place was our living room, most of our meal and leisure time was spent there. It was big, for a backpacking trip, maybe an 8x10 foot footprint, and 8 feet tall in the middle of the gabled roof. Big enough for two folding tables, and nine folding chairs, one person sitting at the head of the table opposite the doorway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/IMG_6694-mess.JPG&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Our mess tent, breakfast on day 2&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We checked out the mess tent, and most of us headed to our individual tents to get out of our boots, and off our feet for a bit. As soon as the mess tent was mostly empty, I got my doctor&amp;rsquo;s appointment out of the way. Tommy was sitting in there alone, so I told him I had a weird rash on my foot, and he just said &amp;ldquo;let&amp;rsquo;s see it&amp;rdquo;. I showed him, and he confirmed my best guess, an allergic reaction to some mystery contact. He pulled out his pharmacy bag, gave me a prednisone, and told me to take half of it. I stopped worrying about the rash, and it wasn&amp;rsquo;t a problem after that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In all the preparation I did for the trip, none of it was research on the terrain, or the camp, or the routine. There are probably a thousand blog posts like this one that I could have read, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t even look for them. I wanted it to be my trip, my own fresh experiences. I just learned what I needed to make sure I&amp;rsquo;d get through it all. So I had no idea how much the porters would be doing for us, how comfortable camp would be. Relative to a normal camping trip, that is. For example, before the trip I asked a bunch of questions, including how I would be carrying my own trash. I got a thorough reply, but no answer to that question, so I was prepared for anything. As it turned out, we just had a big trash bag outside the mess tent, which the porters would take care of. This was convenient, if not the best practice for future &amp;ldquo;real&amp;rdquo; backpacking trips.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The standout event of the first night was the porter introduction. Our group of nine hikers was supported by a&amp;hellip; crew? staff? of 31: one lead guide, three assistant guides, one cook, and 26 porters. Our briefing was with two guides, and we met the others during the first day. We didn&amp;rsquo;t interact with the porters much, so we had an introduction ceremony. We went around the big circle, sharing our names, and then the porters sang a few songs for us. I remember one by name: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vUrVeRGo5IM&#34;target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Jambo Bwana&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/IMG_6883-camp-dinner.JPG&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Curry dinner on day 2&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Camp food was another part of the experience that I knew nothing about before the trip. The chef had an elaborate setup for preparing and serving meals, and the dinners were beyond anything I expected. On the first night, we were served salad, soup, potatoes and fish curry. Our chef introduced himself - as Mr. Delicious, I&amp;rsquo;m told, though I don&amp;rsquo;t recall that - with our first real meal. Like any chef I suppose, we mostly interacted with him during meals. He would come in during dinner, ask how the food was, tell us we weren&amp;rsquo;t eating enough, and threaten to feed us more. We had meat at every meal, and didn&amp;rsquo;t think too hard about how that happened. Or about how well the dishes were cleaned. They made the mistake of serving KJ, who is vegan-ish, a plate of fish, so his entree was tabasco rice that night. He had to explain his dietary restrictions in more depth, and they were fine after that. He had a stash of protein shakes, knowing that this situation was likely. Funny, he seemed to pack lighter than the rest of us, despite carrying a bunch of his own food.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Around dinner and breakfast most days, we&amp;rsquo;d have our health check. Richard would go around the table, ask each of us in turn about headache, dizziness, appetite, and then put a little device on our finger to check our pulse and blood oxygen level. If symptoms were bad enough, pulse high enough, or oxygen low enough, we would have a problem. Fortunately, nobody got AMS too bad. Tommy joked about violating health privacy laws, since everyone would just sit and watch everyone elses&#39; health checks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As expected, I didn&amp;rsquo;t have much trouble with my appetite, or with drinking enough water. The guides encouraged us to drink five liters of water every day, and I had trained myself to do that with no trouble. I think three or four of us were able to eat and drink as much as we needed, but some of us barely felt like eating or drinking at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why not bring breathing equipment, you might ask? I guess there&amp;rsquo;s something called the &amp;ldquo;death zone&amp;rdquo; above about 26000 feet, and I don&amp;rsquo;t know if that&amp;rsquo;s the conventional limit, or people just do any climbs they can manage, or what. It&amp;rsquo;s probably prohibitively expensive. It&amp;rsquo;s possible to buy disposable canned oxygen, though I&amp;rsquo;m not sure if they really work. Supposedly, if a guide catches you using one of these on the hike, they have to take you down immediately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/IMG_7268-tent.JPG&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;My giant messy pile is on the right&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We retired at 7 or 8, and started figuring out our personal tent situations for the first night. I shared with KJ, Andrea with Donna, Chen with Joanne, Natalie with other Joanne, and Tommy by himself. We&amp;rsquo;d sleep in the middle of the tent, with all our stuff shoved off to one side. Even this was sort of luxurious compared to my normal camping routine. I&amp;rsquo;m used to a small tent that barely fits two people, so having room to throw stuff around and repack a little was pretty nice. The first night, I slept pretty well, only waking up for a few hours in the middle of the night. Our rented sleeping bags were huge, very warm, and I didn&amp;rsquo;t even zip it up at first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/IMG_6856-toilet-tent.JPG&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Real flushing action!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s one big aspect of camp left to describe: the toilet situation. Andrea rolled her eyes when I showed her my photo of our camp&amp;rsquo;s toilet tent, but I couldn&amp;rsquo;t leave out such a critical detail. Before the trip, I expected the worst, digging holes for toilets and re-covering them. I figured that&amp;rsquo;s a normal backcountry hike thing, and Kandoo calls themselves &amp;ldquo;leave no trace&amp;rdquo;, which I interpret faithfully. At some point, I was told we would have &amp;ldquo;buckets&amp;rdquo;, so I thought that meant using the toilet would involve less manual labor, but still be pretty gross.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, the facilities we used were the best toilets without running water that I can imagine. Two clean, white plastic, separate compartments that attach to form a thing that functions like a real toilet. The top is a bowl with a seat, a lid, and a hand-pumped flush mechanism, and the bottom is the reservoir. The porters would then take this and dump it into the squat toilets that are available at each camp. These are just big septic tanks that eventually get covered and replaced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the second day, some combination of the food, water, and elevation started to get to my stomach. Nothing too bad, but I had some uncommonly loose bowels. So you can appreciate why I tried to hold it through the entire five-hour hike, hoping to make it all the way to camp without pooping on the trail. I, personally, hoped to avoid that entirely unless really necessary, and I did. Clearly, there were many other hikers who weren&amp;rsquo;t so lucky - you could smell it often enough. Although we discussed our bathroom habits openly, I didn&amp;rsquo;t talk much with anyone in our group about that aspect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/IMG_6726-photo-op-1.JPG&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Standing on a rocky overlook, my favorite&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We woke up early, packed up our stuff, and left our duffel bags in a pile on the tarp in the middle of camp. The tents were put up and taken down by the porters, but the sleeping bags seemed to be our responsibility. After the first night, we tried to roll them up to get them into their stuff sacks, which was pretty tough. After the third or fourth night, I gave up on getting mine in, and left it for the porters to take care of. Nobody seemed to have a problem with that. Later I laerned that rolling it up wasn&amp;rsquo;t right, I should have just been stuffing it into the sack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hike of day 2 started out below the treeline, and continued above it, though not above all the plants. Fortunate, because it gets dusty as hell when that happens. For the remaining days, we&amp;rsquo;d be breathing dust most of the time, which was rough. Early on, we passed a big boulder that rose up high enough to see everything, which made a great photo op spot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spotted a helipad for the first time. The mountain is a huge source of tourism income, so safety for tourists is a big deal. Helipads were made out of painted rocks, close to some of the camps. Later on, we would see a helicopter coming in, presumably to pick someone up, and a bunch of stretchers. The other interesting bit of infrastructure near the camps was the cell towers, which we would see close to camp. Our tour package included daily updates posted to facebook, and I had wondered how that was possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/rescue.jpg&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Safety first&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the first few days, we all had to learn a bit of Swahili. I arrived knowing one word: pole (slowly). Before long, we learned some more basics: ahsante/karibu (thanks/welcome), mambo vipi/poa (what&amp;rsquo;s up/cool), jambo (hello). I also knew hakuna matata (no worries), but I did not know the pronunciation (in Tanzania at least) - it&amp;rsquo;s not &amp;ldquo;ma-TA-duh&amp;rdquo; like they say in the movies, but &amp;ldquo;ma-ta-ta&amp;rdquo;, with both ~t~ s fully annunciated, and the emphasis shared between the last two syllables. I didn&amp;rsquo;t learn much more than that, sadly; I suppose I was preoccupied. As soon as we met our guides, one thing about their speech patterns stood out to me, I think dialect is the right term. They would consistently add some suffixes to certain words, usually ~-u~ or ~-i~ ; the one example I can recall is campu. I wondered if these suffixes have a use in Swahili that matches how they&amp;rsquo;re added to English words, or if, say, the ~mp~ sound is just normally accompanied by the ~u~ suffix in Swahili. I wanted to ask, but didn&amp;rsquo;t trust myself to do so tactfully.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The big event of day 2 was the bonus hike. With our base at Shira camp, we did a short hike to Shira cave, where our guide pointed out a few things, and we rested on top of a little rocky tower. I expected to do more of these acclimatization hikes, but this was the only one, and it was short without much elevation gain. Maybe we spent too long getting to camp on the other days. Tommy sat this one out, which seemed fair. We returned to camp, ate dinner, went to sleep. By night 2, it was actually cold, and I started wearing more layers and zipping up my bag.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/IMG_6961-lava-tower-nap.JPG&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tommy napping at lava tower camp&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Day 3 was rough for many of us. Seven miles over nine hours, and over 3300 feet of climbing - less than day 1 - but to a maximum height of over 15000 feet, the highest elevation many of us had ever reached. &amp;ldquo;Hike high, sleep low&amp;rdquo;, they say, and day 3 exemplifies that strategy. AMS was certainly part of the problem for some of us, and the diarrhea and dust didn&amp;rsquo;t help. One of the girls in our group had an especially bad day, so we gave her lots of drugs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was the only day my Lake Louise AMS evaluation score ever went above zero (six is the first problem threshold), and it was only one, from a mild but persistent headache. With the guides setting the pace for me, I wasn&amp;rsquo;t wearing myself out the way I had in Colorado. The day wasn&amp;rsquo;t so bad for me, but I felt bad for the majority of our group who weren&amp;rsquo;t as lucky. Andrea wondered how I had the energy to pick up some trash to put in a guide&amp;rsquo;s trash bag.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the day&amp;rsquo;s hike, we ascended to the lava tower, stopped at the mini-camp there for lunch, then descended back down almost as far as we climbed to our night camp. This means all the work the porters did to set up and take down camp, they did twice in one day. When we arrived, half of the group collapsed. Exhausted and sick, and seeing camp &amp;ldquo;just past the next rise&amp;rdquo; for what seemed like hours, we needed a real break. Joanne had it the worst, she laid down in the dirt and passed out. She had no idea that guides were rolling her over to put a sleeping mat underneath her.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/IMG_6964-lava-tower.JPG&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The lava tower itself&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the lava tower itself came into view, I asked Kisima if we could climb it, and he said maybe we could. It seemed feasible; I thought we had more acclimatization hikes planned, and this would be an easy way to get another hundred meters or so. At camp, I asked again, Kisima told me to ask lead guide Richard, and he laughed at me. I think he said it used to be OK to climb, but it was no longer allowed. Kisima was havin&#39; a laugh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At camp, hot water was available for washing up. So far, I was committed to the camp life, only washing with wet wipes and sanitizer. I also have a general aversion to being personally served by people (like pedicures, just weird), so having a guy prepare hot water for me, hold a soap bottle for me, etc, felt wrong. After the hike of day 3, I got over all that. I stole someone else&amp;rsquo;s idea, and used the basin for a foot bath - another general first for me, actually. Afterward, I would use the hot water for my hands and face a few times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By day 3 or 4, we had developed something of a routine, in terms of pace and grouping. Prior to the trip, my impression was that we would stay together as one group, moving at the pace of the slowest hiker. I had also read that some operators would allow splitting up into two smaller groups, faster and slower, though I was told that Kandoo doesn&amp;rsquo;t do this. Maybe that&amp;rsquo;s their official policy, but we really didn&amp;rsquo;t follow it. On the normal hiking days, we would pslit up into two or three groups, or even just fan out along the trail, as long as we were all between the front and rear guides. Some of us tended to the front, others to the back. I moved around sort of at random, talking with one group then moving forward or backward to hang with different people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Earlier in the day, I saw a guide carrying Joanne&amp;rsquo;s hydration bladder next to her so she could drink from it. Somehow it got a tiny puncture, so they piled some duct tape on it and had the guide carry it, the only apparent solution. I decided I should fix it, and eventually realized that my waterproof fabric tape might do the trick. That evening, I took my repair kit out and got to work. The hole was just next to the plastic ring that the lid screws into, very hard to reach, but at least close to the top. I had to cut some specific shapes to get the tape in there, but I figured it out, and as far as I know the fix worked for the rest of the trip. It was sometime around then that I found out Tommy&amp;rsquo;s bladder AND nalgene both broke on the first day, and he threw them out, unfortunately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I made my first attempt at some night photography, but the cold forced me to give up pretty quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/IMG_6988-groundsel-tree-270.JPG&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is a single plant, and it&amp;rsquo;s big&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Approaching Barranco camp at the end of the day&amp;rsquo;s hike, we passed some of the weirdest flora I&amp;rsquo;ve ever seen. &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dendrosenecio&#34;target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Giant groundsels&lt;/a&gt; look like mutant palm trees that grew extra arms. We&amp;rsquo;d seen some smaller examples of these earlier, which stood out as strange bushes, but the older ones are bizarre, really alien looking. I was obsessed with these for a few hours, and the further we descended, the bigger and weirder they got.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/IMG_7034-barranco-wall-wide.JPG&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Glare-filled picture of the Barranco wall, as we started&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Day 4 was the most fun for me, but don&amp;rsquo;t tell Donna. We started with the Barranco wall climb, one of the steeper and more hands-on parts of the hike. I&amp;rsquo;ve read it described as a &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yosemite_Decimal_System#Classes&#34;target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;class 4&lt;/a&gt; scramble, though I would have called it a 3. A fall &amp;ldquo;may well be fatal&amp;rdquo;, but the chance of that happening was so low as to be irrelevant. It&amp;rsquo;s certainly a scramble, little bits of climbing punctuating the narrow switchback path. The guides warned us to stay in a tight group and avoid taking breaks, since the constant traffic on the wall path would slow us down otherwise. Donna said she would rather give birth five more times than do this segment of the hike again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/IMG_7051-barranco-climbing.JPG&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Climbing up the wall&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not long after reaching the top of the wall, we found one of the best photo op locations of the hike. Just a big, flat area, with the mountain peak clearly visible in one direction, and the sea of clouds in the other. We took lots of photos here, and I&amp;rsquo;m sure I have more of myself on someone else&amp;rsquo;s phone. Hopefully I can get some of those eventually. In retrospect, we should have taken more photos with the mountain as the background, instead of the clouds; that&amp;rsquo;s why we were there after all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/IMG_7108-photo-op-2.JPG&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Photo op spot 2&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We made it to camp around 1:30, relatively early. I was with Donna and Richard, and he just sped ahead to our site while we went to the bathroom or something. The campground was another huge clearing full of dozens of groups, and without a guide, we had no idea where our site was. Having seen the direction he headed, I was able to spot him by his yellow rain cover from the top of a nearby hill. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t too worried, but Donna was understandably ticked off about this. After settling in, we took out Andrea&amp;rsquo;s cards, and played a few games of rummy, bullshit and crazy 8s. I think this was also the night that Donna had a brush with death. While in the mess tent, sitting right behind me and to the left, Donna started having a bad coughing fit, and I slowly realized that something serious might be happening. Thinking she was about to throw up, I started moving out of the way, when everyone else started getting up as well. Tommy ran around the table in the cramped tent, and started doing the Heimlich maneuver. Donna explained that she got some tea in her windpipe, and she just couldn&amp;rsquo;t fix it herself. It was scary for about 30 seconds, then just funny, as Donna calmed down and laughed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/IMG_7178-ghost.JPG&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ghost Alan&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most nights, I would get a few hours of decent sleep, wake up and read for a few hours, then get another few hours of sleep. Some combination of the cold, the uncomfortable ground, the altitude, and needing to pee, kept me from sleeping through the night pretty consistently. On the fourth night, after a location tip from Kisima, I made plans to get a few good night shots. I woke up in the middle of the night, put on a few more layers of clothes, got my camera stuff ready, and left the tent. From the previous night, I had a decent idea what settings might work in the light of the full moon, but I still had to experiment. Between fidgeting with the tripod and the camera settings, and the long exposure time, I spent about 15 minutes taking pictures until I was pretty sure I had one I liked. Not a great shot of the night sky, but I can do that anywhere. I&amp;rsquo;m pretty happy with this one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not sure if I told anyone about this, but it was some time around here that guide Tila pointed out a couple of his favorite trail landmarks. I took no photos of boobs rock and vagina waterfall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/IMG_7197-rock-window.JPG&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Andrea through the looking-rock&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Day 5 was a chill-out day. A short hike, two miles, three hours. We had the summit climb the next day, so if nothing else we just needed to get to camp early enough to get some rest (in theory). Not a long day of hiking, but something amazing happened. Kisima, watching me with my camera out all the time, started calling me &amp;ldquo;Mr. Sniper&amp;rdquo;. For whatever reason, he specifically took notice of me when I was taking pictures, like the one of Andrea above. Later that day, when Joanne noticed some tents way up on the next ridge, I reached up to grab my glasses off of my shirt collar, so I could see the tents too. They were gone, because putting your glasses on your collar while hiking is a stupid thing to do. I mentioned that they were gone, but realized it was hopeless and just told everyone not to worry about it. Kisima wondered if they had fallen off when I bent down to get that photo, and he turned around and headed down the mountain. Later on, he approached me, made a sad face and shrugged, then pulled the glasses out of his vest pocket. So, that&amp;rsquo;s one way to earn an extra tip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I continued picking up litter as much as I could, and it was on day 5 that I spotted an empty single-serving container of a liquor called Konyagi. At an elevation of 14000 feet, someone decided they couldn&amp;rsquo;t take another step without a shot of whatever this stuff is. I assume it was a guide, which made this litter both sad and impressive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/IMG_7203-hiker-ridge.JPG&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Up they go&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There wasn&amp;rsquo;t all that much that stood out about the terrain or anything on day 5, but the ridge photo is one of my favorites to show the magnitude of the operation. So many people, all the time. There were also some interesting caches of rocks in a few places. Night 5&amp;rsquo;s Barafu camp was a mess. This is the last base camp before the summit, which means the location is more important than the conditions. In other words, it&amp;rsquo;s in a place where you would otherwise never think to make a camp. It&amp;rsquo;s a rocky, dusty slope, with uneven ground and obstructions all over the place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Day 6, we summited. I wrote too much about that, so it&amp;rsquo;s another &lt;a href=&#34;../tanzania-3&#34;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe the porters took this opportunity to resupply; while we spent most of a day going up and back down to the same camp, they had a chance to go most of the way back down the mountain, get rid of some trash, and pick up more food and water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;descent&#34;&gt;Descent&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Afterward, at our last night of camp, we had another round of songs from the guides, and a closing speech from one representative of the group, which turned out to be Tommy. He did us proud, and then we proceeded with the &amp;ldquo;tipping ceremony&amp;rdquo;, which mostly just means distributing our envelopes full of cash to the two groups, guides and porters. We were given very clear tip suggestions: $53 per hiker, to the guides and cook ($12/day, or $20 for the lead guide), and $101 per hiker, to the porters ($5/day). I don&amp;rsquo;t know how much we gave in the end, but I think it was higher than the recommendation. Apparently the lead guide was a bit offended that he didn&amp;rsquo;t get the most money; many of us felt that some of the assistant guides did a better job than he did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With all the trouble we had with summit day hiking, we stopped at Millenium camp, AKA High camp, instead of continuing a bit further to Mweka camp. Brushing my teeth that night, I spotted a wild dog or something snooping around camp, not 15 feet away from me. In the time it would have taken me to find a camera, it vanished.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Day 7, even though we had a few extra miles to go, I think we were all in great spirits that morning. Tommy and KJ disappeared, wanting to get down as fast as possible. We took a brief break at Mweka camp, and continued down through the forest. Everyone was ready to be done, and our heads were down, descending carefully. This was the only time we got any rain; it was light but lasted a few hours. Since we were on our way down, and it was warm, I decided I could manage without my rain jacket. The guides disagreed, pulled an extra rain jacket out of their packs, and more or less made me wear it. I kept it on for a while then tied it around my waist. No rain at all would have been annoying, having carried my rain gear in my day pack all day every day. At any other time it would have been a pain in the ass, but halfway done with the descent, it didn&amp;rsquo;t bother me at all. Plus, it gave me a chance to play the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FTQbiNvZqaY&#34;target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;one song&lt;/a&gt; on my playlist. One memorable quote from Joanne, when talking about breakfast fast food chains: &amp;ldquo;Youse Americans love your trash, don&amp;rsquo;t you&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/IMG_7430-beer-coffee.JPG&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Andrea, dangerously close to coffee withdrawal&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We got to the bottom, we had a bunch of beers in a little pavilion, and had a good sit. After a stop at the gift shop (where I saw a guy with an ubuntu-logo-pattern shirt) and a quick bus ride, we made it back to the hotel, and had our certificate ceremony. We finally relaxed for a bit, then headed out early the next morning for our safari, also another &lt;a href=&#34;../tanzania-4&#34;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;problems&#34;&gt;Problems&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, the hike went remarkably well. Yes, we were supported by four professional guides, and 26 porters to carry everything for us, but still. My introduction to backpacking was a seven-day trek to 19000 feet, and I made it through relatively unscathed. Of course, there were a few problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two big scares I had right at the beginning, &lt;a href=&#34;../tanzania-1/#medical&#34;&gt;rabies&lt;/a&gt; and a mystery rash, ultimately had no effect on me. I figured the rabies risk was nil from the beginning, and I&amp;rsquo;m glad to report I did not get rabies. The rash, which appeared on my feet just before I left Austin, didn&amp;rsquo;t get much worse. I had no idea what it was - athletes foot, allergic reaction, something else - so I threw everything at it: hydrocortisone, athlete&amp;rsquo;s foot cream, claritin. Then, on day 1 of the hike, I found out that Tommy, one of our group, was a doctor. Not just that, he had a &amp;ldquo;pharmacy bag&amp;rdquo; in his day pack. I was hesitant to ask, not wanting to burden him with a patient in the middle of his trip, but he was very accommodating. I explained what my problem, and he said &amp;ldquo;Let&amp;rsquo;s see it&amp;rdquo;, so I showed him. Just some allergic reaction, apparently. One I&amp;rsquo;ve never had before, with no discernible cause, that popped up right before the longest, most remote physical activity of my life. I kept it wrapped up, and Tommy gave me a course of prednisone. It didn&amp;rsquo;t clear up immediately, but it stopped irritating me, so problem solved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then there were a handful of other minor medical nuisances: small cuts, broken fingernails, one little blister. The only issue here was that my bandaids were rapidly being consumed for the stupid foot rash, so I didn&amp;rsquo;t have as many as I would have liked to deal with minor stuff on my hands. Having decent gauze would have helped. I knew to trim my toenails just before the hike, it&amp;rsquo;s important to keep them short when they&amp;rsquo;re being compressed all day long in your boots. I skipped the fingers. I tend to keep my fingernails longer, but I should have cut them all the way back for this trip. I broke one thumbnail particularly badly, right at the beginning, and had to keep dirty bandaids on it the whole time. I expected more blisters, only needed a blister pad for one or two days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/2018-09-24-06.37.44-morning-cocktail.jpg&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;My morning cocktail&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m glad I came prepared. Tommy was the pharmacy, but it was still good to have some drugs spread out among different people. Natalie had one awful sick day, and we just threw drugs at her. I ended up giving her all my immodium and cipro - I had six cipro and she had two, even though she had another three months in the country! I hope she doesn&amp;rsquo;t need any.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also had the one chance to use my sweet repair kit. On day 2 or 3, Joanne&amp;rsquo;s water bladder sprung a leak, and her duct tape patch wasn&amp;rsquo;t getting the job done. I found out because one of the guides was carrying her bladder upright, next to her. I guess they would have continued like that for the rest of the hike if I hadn&amp;rsquo;t stepped in. I had a strip of Tenacious Tape, which I bought to repair a drybag at Ortlieb&amp;rsquo;s recommendation - seemed like a good option. The hole in the bladder was in the worst place, right next to the rim of the lid - not a lot of surrounding surface area for the tape, and hard to reach. I cut a couple of circular arcs of tape, and attached one to each side of the bladder. I think it lasted for the rest of the hike. Carrying that kit around was worth it, just for this. My regret is that Tommy had the same problem on day 1, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t know, so he got rid of the bladder before I had a chance to fix it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, organization was tough. I think this will come with experience, but I also want to replace my daypack. The giant main chamber is just too big, and the two lid pockets are awkward. I ended up hanging so many things off my belt and shoulder straps to make up for it, which was fine, but I wonder if there is a better way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;returning-to-moshi&#34;&gt;Returning to Moshi&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/IMG_7489-certificate.JPG&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Incontrovertible proof that I made it&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soon after returning to Stella Maris, we headed to the bar to receive our certificates. It was a fitting way to conclude the experience; a nice certificate, a cozy but semi-official ceremony, and one last photo op. Maybe a bit overdone, as the locals seemed to expect us to value the certificates more than we did. Tommy left his behind, and someone at the hotel freaked out, expecting him to come back to pick it up. Natalie stayed for the ceremony, and then left for her next obligation, teaching at a girls&#39; school in Moshi. She had delayed a taxi a few hours to join the ceremony, so when it ended she had to get out of there quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Totally done with the trek, I had a chance to shower. I knew the shower was done because I got all the way through the one bar of soap I had with me. Taking that shower was fantastic, despite being one of the worst physical shower setups I&amp;rsquo;ve ever used. Tommy decided to go into town to get a shave and a haircut, but I declined his offer to join; I suppose I wanted to be a mountain man for a few more days. I repacked, and finished writing the postcard I had bought earlier (I may have taken some inspiration from Andrea&amp;rsquo;s). I had a little laundry to do, as well as a handful of things I wanted to donate to the porters. I brought the laundry and donations to the front desk, filled out a laundry list, and left, assured that my clothes would be dropped off at my door by 6am the next day. Back in my room, I found one more thing to donate, and took that down to the desk. When I showed it to the guy, he gestured toward the door and said &amp;ldquo;just put it there with the others&amp;rdquo;. I looked at the door - the main entrance of the hotel - pulled it away from the wall a bit, and saw all of my laundry - some of my best clothes - AND the donations sitting together in a pile. I decided to trust the system, dropped the other donation, and walked away. Andrea found out about this and said &amp;ldquo;your clothes are gone&amp;rdquo;. That scared me, but sure enough, at 6am the next morning, I had them all back, delivered to my room. Hakuna matata.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/IMG_7514-shower-270.JPG&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The silliest shower&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a general tendency to notice problems. I don&amp;rsquo;t mean to complain; I thoroughly enjoyed every part of this trip. It&amp;rsquo;s just that, when I think back on an experience like this, try to recall the little things, I do remember is the weird stuff. Design flaws, silly rules, poor planning, they just stand out to me. I don&amp;rsquo;t need to enumerate these minor nuisances that I noticed, but they might be a succinct way to record some of the impressions I had about the second part of our trip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One example: dinner at Stella Maris. Our last night there, we ordered dinner as a group. We knew from previous meals that their kitchen isn&amp;rsquo;t too fast, so we were ready to order early. We also knew that ordering in advance for dinner at 8 means they will start cooking your order at 8. Most of us were still dealing with returning to civilization, bouncing back and forth between bedrooms and the bar. I walked down to the dining room to give my dinner order, plus Andrea&amp;rsquo;s. Everyone else placed their orders from their seats in the bar, and I informed the server that I&amp;rsquo;d be eating in the bar with them. When dinner time came around, it was chaos, getting the right orders out took forever. Even after that, half of us had no silverware. None of this was a problem at all; we were relaxing in our hotel, enjoying the company. I just don&amp;rsquo;t understand it. This hotel exists to cater to western tourists, and they seemed to make a genuine effort to design their services around that. But somehow, they don&amp;rsquo;t have a great idea how to run a restaurant effectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other examples: the showers don&amp;rsquo;t make sense. Dinner service at our safari lodge was also strange, in a different way. The service staff there tried too hard to be familiar and attentive, to the point of aggravation (&amp;ldquo;Hi Alan what&amp;rsquo;s up!&amp;rdquo; every 10 minutes while I&amp;rsquo;m eating or in the middle of a conversation is not good service). The communication of our transportation and meal plans at the beginning of our safari was poor. Again, none of these were real problems, just odd experiences. Much of it felt like best guesses at what westerners want, that were just a bit off the mark. Or maybe, like people are kind of high most of the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Probably just my American expectations, failing me on the odd occasion that I venture out into the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;returning-home&#34;&gt;Returning home&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We caught a brief glimpse of the mountain on our night drive to the airport. It would have been nice to get one good view of it from the ground, but I&amp;rsquo;ll settle for the closeup view we did get.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m amazed that they can support such a volume of tourists with an airport so close to the mountain. We got checked in pretty quickly, but it was so chaotic. We arrived and got in the one big line going out the door, soon realizing that was because there is an x-ray machine right in the middle of the single entrance to the building. We shoved our bags through, and I&amp;rsquo;m not sure if anyone was even watching them. A security dude at the entrance asked Donna where she was going, she answered, and he asked &amp;ldquo;Are you SURE?&amp;rdquo;, so she just said yes. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t allowed to pass him until I could tell him my flight confirmation number.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/2018-10-01-10.02.07-rainbow.jpg&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A greeting from the sky in Amsterdam&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After making it through the checkin process, we chilled out. Actually, only half of us made it through before a ticket printer broke, so the Americans ordered some food and beer while waiting for the Brits. There weren&amp;rsquo;t a lot of other places for us to go anyway; it&amp;rsquo;s a tiny airport with one small souvenir shop area, and one restaurant/bar. Past the security check was one more bar, and &amp;ldquo;eight&amp;rdquo; gates, right next to each other, that all led directly to the tarmac. We found some seats in that area, and struggled to understand the PA announcements about how to choose your gate. When boarding time came, it was sort of a free-for-all anyway. I think we were on a 777, which was almost as big as the JRO terminal (not joking). A short hop to Dar es Salaam, a quick layover there, and we were on our way home. We went through security in Amsterdam, which was unbelievably efficient. We said our goodbyes, and the four subgroups parted ways. As boarding started, I noticed a rainbow in one corner of a window. When I went to check it out, I realized it was one of the brightest I&amp;rsquo;ve seen - not just a double rainbow, but a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.atoptics.co.uk/rainbows/supers.htm&#34;target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;supernumerary&lt;/a&gt;, at least over some portion of the arc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/2018-10-01-21.19.45-holding-pattern.jpg&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I think they call this a holding pattern&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like to bring a laptop when I fly, it&amp;rsquo;s one of the most productive environments for me, discomfort notwithstanding. I didn&amp;rsquo;t bring one on this trip, and I had used Andrea&amp;rsquo;s a few times, but she had time-sensitive work to do on the return flights. So at this point, I had gotten plenty of sleep, read two books (Expanse 4 and 5), watched eight movies and a bunch of TV shows (Solo, Mark Felt, Game Night, Legally Blonde, Infinity War, Jumanji, Disaster Artist, Rampage, The Pizza Show, Trial and Error), tried all the lame videogames on the entertainment system (I even played battleship with Andrea while we sat in adjacent seats), and I was simply out of things to do. I&amp;rsquo;m not accustomed to long-haul flights, and we&amp;rsquo;d been in an airport or plane for close to thirty hours when we learned about a weather delay in Houston, so we wandered aimlessly around the Texas sky for another hour. This was agonizing, I don&amp;rsquo;t remember the last time I felt so anxious. We made it to Houston eventually, and all the lines were mercifully short.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;technical-notes&#34;&gt;Technical Notes&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basic hike track stats, from my phone:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;hike&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;miles&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;start time&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;end time&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;hours&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;M1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6.65&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10:57am&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4:39pm&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5:41&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;M2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3.42&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8:16am&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1:26pm&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5:09&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;M2 bonus&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0.91&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4:25pm&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5:42pm&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1:17&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;M3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7.1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8:22am&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5:29pm&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9:07&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;M4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3.37&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8:28am&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1:18pm&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4:50&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;M5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.25&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8:49am&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12:03pm&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3:14&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;M6 summit&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6.17&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12:09am&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10:12am&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10:02&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;M6 descent&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.65&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3:15pm&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5:15pm&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2:00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;M7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7.47&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7:49pm&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1:03pm&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5:14&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;-&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;-&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;total&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;39.99&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And some elevation numbers. Some of the steepest climbing we did was offset later in the same hike, especially the summit climb, which was almost perfectly symmetric. The last column here is the average grade of the main climbing segment of those hikes. The hikes with blanks there were more or less monotonic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;hike&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;start feet&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;max feet&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;end feet&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;total ascent&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;total descent&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;avg grade&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;avg grade (climb)&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;M1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6014&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9869&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9839&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4829&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1006&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10.9%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;M2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9957&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12697&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12490&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3019&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;487&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;14.0%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;M2 bonus&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12513&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12740&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12516&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;315&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;315&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0.1%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;16.4%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;M3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12543&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;15236&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12976&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3377&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2935&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.2%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10.7%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;M4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;13064&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;13832&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;13146&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2133&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2058&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0.5%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;19.3%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;M5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;13159&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;15256&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;15253&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2201&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;107&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;17.6%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;M6 summit&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;15144&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;19281&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;15154&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4253&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4266&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0.0%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;28.3%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;M6 descent&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;15121&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;15148&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12405&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;114&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2830&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;-19.4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;M7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12369&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12454&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5322&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;414&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7464&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;-17.9%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;-&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;-&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;ndash;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;ndash;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;-&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;total&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;20655&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;21468&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sleep&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Night 1: Bed 8 or 9 pm. Wake for 1-2 hours around midnight, read, wake 5:30am.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Night 2: Bed 8 or 9 pm. Wake 12 - 4, sleep till 6am.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Night 3: Bed 8:40p. Wake 1a, sleep 4a to 6a. Sit pad as sleeping pad under hip.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Night 4: Bed 8:40p. Wake 2 - 4, sleep till 730a.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Night 5: Nap 4-515. Bed 8p, sleep 10-11.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Night 6: Sleep 1015-1215, bed 8:30p wake 6a.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Battery&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day 1: phone tracking only, 50%, full recharge from Anker. Canon 3/3, Garmin 4/4&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day 2: phone 50% with tracking, reading, wikipedia, full recharge from Anker. Canon 3/3, Garmin 4/4&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day 3: phone down to 45%, mostly tracking, Canon 2/3, Garmin 3/4. Not much charge from solar panel. Started putting batteries in sleeping bag at night.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day 4: phone down to 70% , mostly tracking. Some solar charge at early camp. Canon 1/3 at night, but back up to 2/3 by morning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day 5: phone 80% all tracking, Canon 1/3, Garmin 2/4&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day 6: changed Garmin and headlamp to lithium batteries. Canon back up to 2/3 when warm. phone 40% after summit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Health and drugs&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day 1: pred 5mgx2, Claritin; minor nausea&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day 2: pred 10, diamox 125, Claritin, Pepto x4; minor nausea&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day 3: pred 10 diamox 125, Claritin, Pepto x4; headache, sore ankle, glute, one small blister&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day 4: pred 10 diamox 250x2, Claritin, Pepto x4; glute, numb big toe started while sleeping&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day 5: pred 10 diamox 250x2, Claritin, Pepto x2&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day 6: pred 5, diamox 250, Pepto x2, malaria&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day 7: pred 5, Pepto x2, malaria&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clothes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day 1: gray Icebreaker shirt, OR sleeves, gray buff, smartwool boxers, beige pants, cheap Merino socks. sleep pj pants, undershirt, bag unzipped, blow up pillow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day 2: (same as m1 except) blue synthetic underwear, darn tough socks #1. bonus hike, add capilene. sleep Merino base layer, matix, pj pants, bag zipped, blow up pillow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day 3: same, except darn tough #1, smart wool underwear, smart wool base layer. base pants were too much, base top oscillated depending on sun. sleep Merino, matix, pj pants, thin smartwool socks plus big rei socks (big ones too much)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day 4: same except blue boxers, darn tough #2, removed base layer top after Barranco wall. added base layer plus down at camp. sleep same as previous, except cotton briefs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day 5: same except black boxers, darn tough socks (not sure which), added down jacket at camp.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day 6: ice breaker, sun sleeves, smart wool, capilene, down, rain jacket; down hood, both buffs, headlamp; smart wool boxers, long pants, hiking pants, rain pants; darn tough socks, cheap Merino socks. liner gloves, mittens, hand warmers. needed all of it, and toes were still super cold; napped in boxers and t-shirt out side of bag. too hot to stay asleep. second hike, hiking pants, ice breaker, smart wool, rain jacket. sleep ice breaker, smart wool both&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day 7: (rain) ice breaker + sleeves, smart wool, smart wool+smart wool, rain layer; strip down to rain pants and single top layer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I probably brought twice as many articles of clothing as I should have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--

food
sep 20 breakfast buffet; chicken pilipili; coconut milk tilapia (whole fish, pain in the ass)
m1 breakfast buffet, banana soup; box lunch w/ grilled chicken, egg, juice box, biscuit, chocolate; soup, salad, potatoes, fish, curry
m2 omelette, toast, sausage; spaghetti, carrot soup, oranges; pumpkin soup, ...
m3 porridge, banana toast, crepes, bacon, eggs; veggie soup, boiled egg, veggie burger, chicken, salad, fries; zucchini soup, mashed potatoes, spaghetti, veggie curry, green beans, beef, warm pineapple slices. are very little lunch and breakfast from fear of diarrhea, ate Large dinner
m4 crepes, toast, soup; soup, pasta salad, kale stuff, local dish ugali or whatever, chicken, oranges; soup, beef veggie curry
m5 ate 3 snack bar at 4a, beans toast granola eggs oranges; soup, salad, fries, beef kebabs 230; soup, spaghetti, apples 530
m6 tiny bowl of porridge before summit, probably 1500 calories of snacks during hike; soup, burrito thing, tuna toast, egg; banana stew
m7 pancakes, toast

poo
m1 none
m2 after breakfast, after arrival, after dinner, wake at midnight (a little runny), 3am (mostly gas)
m3 8p (solid but messy), 1a urgent but solid
m4 none
m5 730p good, 11p small right before summit
m6 none
m7 3p, 430p (hotel)

nausea
m1 late start getting nausea burps
m2 midnight wake get a few midnight burps
m3 burps are fine in morning. egg at lunch made one or two gross burps, then fine
m4 no trouble
m5 no trouble
m6 no trouble
m7

postcard: I&#39;m writing from Stella Maris hotel at the base of mount Kilimanjaro. I just summited the mountain, and it was the hardest thing I&#39;ve ever done. dream big and know that you can do anything!

mambo vipi - what&#39;s up?
poa - cool
Asante - thanks
karibu - welcome
Jambo - hello
pole - slowly
hakuna matata - no worries

--&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tanzania 3: Summit</title>
      <link>http://alanbernstein.github.io/posts/tanzania-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://alanbernstein.github.io/posts/tanzania-3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I climbed a mountain with &lt;a href=&#34;http://andrearobertson.com/&#34;target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Andrea&lt;/a&gt; and Donna. A couple days before we summited, Andrea said it was the stupidest thing she&amp;rsquo;d ever done. I didn&amp;rsquo;t disagree.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a very long blog post, split into five parts. If you aren&amp;rsquo;t sure how far you&amp;rsquo;ll get, read parts 3 and 4, then 2, then maybe 1. Part 5 is mostly for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../tanzania-1&#34;&gt;1: prep&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;a href=&#34;../tanzania-2&#34;&gt;2: hike&lt;/a&gt; - 3: summit - &lt;a href=&#34;../tanzania-4&#34;&gt;4: safari&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;a href=&#34;../tanzania-5&#34;&gt;5: post-mortem&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;a href=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/trips/kili&#34;target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;slide show (upcoming)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;video autoplay loop width=700px src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/kili-summit-relive-cut.webm&#34;&gt;&lt;/video&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Looks easy, now&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, time for the big climb. This is the part that Zach described as the hardest thing he&amp;rsquo;d ever done. I was skeptical, not from confidence in my ability, but from having a very specific, previously existing &amp;ldquo;hardest thing&amp;rdquo;. In July 2015, Kevin and I biked 450+ miles across Northern California, self supported, with no proper training (for me I mean, Kevin knew what he was doing). I thought my daily bike commute at the time, 10 miles one way and hilly, was enough to prepare me, and I was so wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is something qualitatively different about the experience of being on a bike for an entire day, and most of that difference is just physical pain. My hands went numb, my butt hurt from sitting all day, I changed my position every 10 minutes in hopes of finding a less painful one. My knees were the worst. Halfway through, I thought I would have to give up, afraid that continuing to stress my knees would do irreversible damage. By the end, I was literally limping, which I had never done on a bike before. Thankfully, with one rest day and a couple shorter days near the end, one of my knees had enough life left in it to get me all the way there. Kevin did the only thing that makes sense in that situation: pushed me to keep going, despite all my crying. I thought he was being an asshole, he couldn&amp;rsquo;t understand how bad it was, he just wanted to finish the ride for his own sake. Now, I&amp;rsquo;m glad he didn&amp;rsquo;t help me figure out how to hitch a ride somewhere. It&amp;rsquo;s funny, on my 2016 Austin-Dallas ride with Wesley, the roles were reversed - I had to become the asshole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, for a good three years, that was clearly the most difficult physical achievement of my life. It was so painful, so drawn out, so desperate, I couldn&amp;rsquo;t imagine that just one day of the Kilimanjaro hike could top it. I was wrong about that too, but not for the reason you might guess.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first five days brought us from 6000 to 15000 feet, most of that for acclimatization. The summit climb, from Barafu camp to Uhuru peak, is 7-8 hours, 3 miles long, and 4000 feet of elevation gain, up to about 19000 feet. At the summit, the air pressure is under 50% of sea level. If you could somehow imagine breathing with only one lung, it would be a fair comparison. Maybe if you smoked cigarettes for 30 years and then tried to run, you could understand the feeling. We started early, so it was also below freezing. We started &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; early, so we had minimal sleep and a meager breakfast. Most of us weren&amp;rsquo;t getting great sleep most nights, but this night was especially rough for me. Between all of these handicaps, I couldn&amp;rsquo;t think straight, which must have kept me from realizing how stupid it was to keep going.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The day before, I knew the plan: go to sleep wearing whatever you can of the under layers that you plan to wear on the climb. Have your pack ready to go. Wake up at 11pm, to finish dressing and eat breakfast. Start the hike at midnight. The guides also decided to split some of the slower hikers into a second group, so that we would hopefully all reach the summit together. Of course, that means they&amp;rsquo;d have to leave earlier, waking at 10pm and leaving at 11. I went to bed around 7 or 8 and, unlike most other nights on the hike, I left my book in my pack. I laid in my sleeping bag, stared at the ceiling of the tent, closed my eyes. I counted sheep. I thought the boringest thoughts. And then, I heard the guides shuffling around outside, brushing on tent doors, to wake up the early group. It was 10pm, and I&amp;rsquo;d had zero sleep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I woke up at 11. I did manage one hour of actual sleep before the guides woke us. I imagined how Lisa would have acted if she had been there with me (100% sure she would not have gotten out of bed, assuming she made it that far). I got dressed, checked my pack, and went out to the mess tent. Every meal prior to this one had been an assortment of items, often one serving dish full of so much food that we couldn&amp;rsquo;t finish it. The guides would come in toward the end of the meal, ask if we were hungry, encourage us to eat more than our fill. But this meal, &amp;ldquo;breakfast&amp;rdquo; before the climb, was just a bowl of porridge. The waiter brought in the pot, we ate a bowl, and that was it. I ate mine plain. Maybe it was too early to cook a real meal. Maybe we wouldn&amp;rsquo;t have had enough time to eat it. Whatever the reasoning, the food I was served was not sufficient for the situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/IMG_1247-layers-90-annotated.JPG&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Everything I wore to brave the eight hours of 19°F mountain air, maybe 5°F with windchill.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--

top:
- ice breaker merino wool t-shirt plus synthetic sun sleeves (I want this to be my bottom layer if I need to strip down for hot weather)
- smartwool 250? long sleeve quarter zip
- patagonia capilene long sleeve
- uniqlo down jacket
- marmot rain jacket/windbreaker

head:
- lightweight wool buff
- midweight synthetic buff
- knit cap and/or down hood (mostly used the down hood)
- headlamp

bottom:
- smartwool merino boxers, smartwool 250? long pants, REI sahara hiking pants, uniqlo blocktech rain pants

hands+feet
- burton liner gloves
- burton heavy mittens with ineffective hand warmers
- darn tough socks
- heavier off-brand merino wool socks
- hiking boots

--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The gear research and shopping we&amp;rsquo;d done, it was all for this. The high performance, packable clothes, all layered together. In Texas I seldom wear more than a single layer; for the summit I wore five on top, four on the bottom, and two on my hands and feet. I don&amp;rsquo;t regret any of it. Somewhere in the first hour, I got warm, lowered my hood, and started thinking about how to start dropping layers. By the second hour, I knew I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t need to figure it out. The only thing I would do differently is to keep my feet warmer somehow; my toes were freezing most of the hike. I don&amp;rsquo;t know how I could have worn more socks, maybe foot warmers are the way to go. It also would have been nice if my rain layer had pass-through pockets; my hiking pants pockets were loaded with snacks, camera gear, etc, and it was a bit of a hassle to get to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/2018-09-25-23.41.51-pre-summit.jpg&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Ready&amp;rdquo; to summit&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, geared up, &amp;ldquo;rested&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;fed&amp;rdquo;, we headed for the summit. Remember that anticlimactic start to the hike on day 1? This was different. This felt surreal, my legs in charge and my mind just along for the ride. Before long, we started seeing people from the early group. Tommy decided to start with them, and he&amp;rsquo;s the one who noticed Joanne&amp;rsquo;s lips and fingers turning blue. That called for a health check, and with dangerously low blood oxygen, she had no choice but to turn back. We all gave her a hug and continued on our way. In the next hour or two, we also passed Andrea and Donna, who were still ascending, just taking it slow. I gave Andrea a hug, Tommy rejoined the main group, and we pressed on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- 
&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/8ybshjE24-g&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
 --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;video width=350px controls src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/summit-night.webm&#34;&gt;&lt;/video&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;At the time, I had no idea I sounded like this, but I&amp;rsquo;m so glad I recorded it&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;rant&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Summit night was stupid. Just miserable. Too tired, too hungry, too cold, too windy, and not enough oxygen. Summiting during the day might be hot, but at least I would&amp;rsquo;ve had a couple extra hours of sleep. I couldn&amp;rsquo;t appreciate the summit because of the cold and exhaustion. I don&amp;rsquo;t think my brain was working properly during the climb, but what few, raw thoughts I had centered on questioning the logic of the night summit. Not questioning my own life decisions that brought me there, but rather the decisions of the park administration who determined that this schedule is the best option. Why does anyone think this a good idea?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if I&amp;rsquo;d had a decent amount of rest and breakfast, I was still subjected to the bitter cold and wind for eight hours. Why not start at 3 or 4am? You&amp;rsquo;d have a decent breakfast, hike in a few hours of miserable cold, then the sun would come out to encourage you to keep going, right in the middle of the climb when you need it most. You could spend a few more minutes appreciating the summit, able to operate a camera with non-frozen fingers, and deal with the heat while descending, when dropping layers isn&amp;rsquo;t such a big deal. The day&amp;rsquo;s whole schedule gets pushed out a few hours, so you end up descending to Mweka camp in the dark. Big deal? Why is that a problem, but ascending to the summit in the dark, with subzero winds, is fine? I don&amp;rsquo;t get it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We asked Kisima about this, and he had some answers. First, he said, in the dark it&amp;rsquo;s hard to see how far away the summit is, so you&amp;rsquo;re less likely to give up out of despair. Maybe a joke, maybe not. On the full moon hike, we could see the summit clearly, but we spent most of the hike looking down at our feet. Second, of course, is the chance to see the sunrise from the summit. Sunrise is great, but you see it from any point on the summit hike.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most importantly, I suspect, discouraging people from hanging out at the summit is a &lt;em&gt;benefit&lt;/em&gt;, from the perspective of park management. Our hike was at one of the most popular times of year, but with even half as many people on the mountain, it&amp;rsquo;s still a logistical puzzle to keep all of them flowing smoothly from camp to camp every day. I also asked Kisima about a hike with a summit day that starts and ends at Barafu camp, the last stop before the summit (as opposed to continuing to descend another 5000 feet, after returning to Barafu camp). The answer was obvious: the camp would have to be twice as big to support such a route. That camp is already the worst site I&amp;rsquo;ve ever seen a tent on, just a dusty, rocky slope. Finding space for another 50-100 tents in that area is, presumably, impossible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All that said, I know there is at least one tour operator with a daytime summit option. I&amp;rsquo;d recommend that, with whatever caveats or higher prices go with it. For a night summit, I&amp;rsquo;d recommend being prepared to use sleeping pills. It may not be logistically possible for summit night.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;/rant&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With such a small breakfast, all those snack bars I brought finally had a purpose. I had eaten some earlier in the hike, two or three scattered throughout the day. This time, I made a meal out of them; I ate 1000-1500 calories of snack bars on the way up. Once an hour or so, I would do the check-your-pockets dance, through three layers on top and two in my pants, trying to find anything I could stuff in my mouth. I finished those, then found a few more in my pack. Every time I ate one, it was because I was starving, and I&amp;rsquo;m not using that word lightly. It&amp;rsquo;s a sensation I don&amp;rsquo;t experience often, like my stomach trying to digest itself. I saved each snack bar until it was unbearable, and I knew I had to eat to keep going.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Exhaustion was an orthogonal problem. The first few hours were fine, then I started to drift. I would close my eyes for just a second, but keep walking. My head started to tilt to the side. In retrospect, it seems obvious that the lack of oxygen was contributing, but at the time I thought I was just extremely tired. If a guide had seen me in that state, I don&amp;rsquo;t know if they would have let me continue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I noticed my headlamp and GPS batteries getting low, so at one of our bathroom breaks, I swapped in some new batteries. Bad idea: you need the headlamp to see, and it&amp;rsquo;s too cold to use your fingers, even for something as simple as changing batteries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was beautiful, though. From the start of the climb, I was tracking the path of the full moon from Mawenzi peak to Uhuru, the time until sunrise, the time until the summit. Around 6:15, we finally saw hints of the sunrise, and I sighed in relief, anticipating the feeling coming back to my toes. That proved to be too hopeful, but at least we could see the mountain in full light. We saw Stella Point, the glaciers, and some crazy snow formations. We saw a sea of clouds in every direction, stretching to the farthest horizon I&amp;rsquo;ve seen outside of an airplane. I thought I spotted a tiny section of the coast, but I&amp;rsquo;m sure that was wishful thinking. That&amp;rsquo;s as much description as I&amp;rsquo;ll attempt, first because it defies words, and second because I was barely conscious at the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/2018-09-26-06.17.01-stella-point.jpg&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t zoom in on my face&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stella point, at 18652 feet high, and on the rim of the Kibo Crater, is the top of the mountain. Anything you can see from the summit, you can see from Stella point. It&amp;rsquo;s an achievement by itself, which is why there&amp;rsquo;s a big sign there. We stopped for a few minutes, and I took a few photos. That makes it sound simple. Actually, I had to pull off both my mittens, attach them somewhere so I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t lose them, take off my liner gloves, and stuff them in a pocket. My camera, hanging off my belt, was accessible, but the battery was deep in a pocket somewhere, hiding from the cold, as was my phone. By the time I had the camera ready to go, my fingers were already halfway to freezing. I gave up on the photos pretty quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/2018-09-26-08.01.50-snow.jpg&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I call these &amp;ldquo;snowlagmites&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From Stella point, we could see Uhuru peak, the highest point on the rim, or at least we saw the end of the line of hikers. The summit seemed so close, but we knew from the last few days that seeing your destination doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean much on the mountain. It didn&amp;rsquo;t matter, there was no way I was going to turn back when I was that close to the summit. Not when I could see it. Guides told us it was just 30 minutes more, because it&amp;rsquo;s their job to lie to us. 80 minutes later, after shuffling through fields of snow stalagmites, I made it to the summit. I waited in the big jumbled line to take a handful of photos at the sign. A few nights before, some of us made signs to hold up for the photos, saying hi to our loved ones, or whatever. None of us cared about them anymore. It was too cold to try to find them in a pack, we&amp;rsquo;d have to wait in the photo line again, it just wasn&amp;rsquo;t worth it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/2018-09-26-07.33.27-uhuru.jpg&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If I look dead, it&amp;rsquo;s because I was&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, after just a few minutes, we started to head back down. Thankfully, the descent was an order of magnitude easier. Not &lt;em&gt;easy&lt;/em&gt;, of course, but it was 2.5 hours of gravity-assisted scree running, versus 7.5 hours of shuffling in the dark. Descending on the scree might have been fun, if I had been more cogent. Actually, I was just desperate for a nap. With the group divided in two on the hardest part of the hike, the guides had brought in a porter, Emmanuel, to act as a fifth guide (two guides for six hikers is risky - when someone turns back on the summit, it can be serious, so a guide goes down with them), and he stayed with my group. The group grew less coherent as the descent went on, some of us going at our own pace. At one point, seeing how sloppy my steps were, Emmanuel asked to carry my pack. I think three of the hikers&#39; packs were being carried by guides at that point (maybe two by Emmanuel), but I declined, just generally paranoid about losing control of my pack while traveling. Of course, he wasn&amp;rsquo;t going to steal anything, but he did drop it on the dusty ground, covering my bite valve with dirt, and screwing up the magnetic clasp. Plus, he had all my water. At the time, this upset me, perhaps irrationally so, and I was probably a bit rude to him. I apologized later, and I figure he understood the situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With 2000+ feet left to descend, I decided I was done waiting for the others. I needed sleep, as soon as possible and for as long as possible. With some of the group still lagging behind, I figured I could stretch our one hour allocated for naps into two, maybe more. &amp;ldquo;No breaks. I need to get down and go to sleep.&amp;rdquo; I said to Emmanuel when he called to me to slow down. I had to wait a few minutes for Richard to catch up to Emmanuel, who cleared him to descend with me. I went down on the scree as fast as I could - not running, for fear of poor coordination with all the exhaustion and hunger - but fast. I had to weave to force myself not to gain too much speed. My $10 rain pants turned out to be a problem, as the slick drawstring wouldn&amp;rsquo;t stay knotted. My third layer of pants kept falling down, and it was all I could do to yank them back up every few minutes. In my mind, stopping to pull them all the way up and secure them just wasn&amp;rsquo;t worth the time. Almost at the bottom, Emmanuel stopped me and pulled them up. I felt like an idiot, but didn&amp;rsquo;t care. One of the guides saved me again here, recovering my lens cap after I lost it without knowing. I only realized it had happened when my lens filter somehow unscrewed itself and fell off onto the dusty ground. That was the one negative of the capture clip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joanne sat at the edge of camp, waiting to greet us. I tried to say hi, but I was probably too out of it to speak properly. As we descended through Barafu camp in the daylight, it became apparent that our group was set up close to the bottom of the camp. Ascending in the dark, all I had seen was the rocks and boots right in front of me, so I had no idea how far we walked through the rest of camp. When my tent was in sight, I headed straight for it, only to be stopped by a porter who insisted on shaking my hand to congratulate me. Another ten porters followed him. Our waiter shoved a big pitcher of juice in my face and said I should drink some. I declined, he insisted, I drank a mug full. I was surprised at how cold it was, so I had another. Then, I crawled into my tent, stripped off as many layers of clothes as I could manage, and passed out. It was 10:30am or so, the intermittent cloud cover dwindling as the day progressed. It was too hot for it, but I managed about two hours of sleep anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I woke up, everyone else was back, failing at sleeping, or hanging out in the mess tent. I don&amp;rsquo;t think anybody substantially disagreed with my sentiments about the climb; everyone was worn out. Some of the girls talked about boycotting the rest of the day&amp;rsquo;s hike. I didn&amp;rsquo;t believe that was a possibility, but rumors of a shorter descent hike started swirling. We discussed the summit, how stupid the schedule was, how badly we all felt. Donna asked what I thought, maybe half expecting me to say it was easy. I told her it was awful, and she looked relieved. Before the trip, Donna wasn&amp;rsquo;t confident she&amp;rsquo;d make it to the summit, but she went all the way. After that, she hired two porters to support her the rest of the way down, descending being much harder on her knees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/2018-09-26-15.52.31-rescue-stretchers.jpg&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note the motorbike tires and full suspension&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the descent from Barafu camp, we saw some stretchers scattered beside the trail, reminding us that it could have been worse. We discussed our shared misery, and joked about the impossible proposition of ever summiting Kilimanjaro again. One of the guides told us about another trek option: summiting in one day, but at the cost of a six-day trek. We didn&amp;rsquo;t discuss it much, but anyone paying attention would have noticed a glint in my eye&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../tanzania-2#descent&#34;&gt;Back to part 2 - the hike&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tanzania 4: Safari</title>
      <link>http://alanbernstein.github.io/posts/tanzania-4/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://alanbernstein.github.io/posts/tanzania-4/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I climbed a mountain with &lt;a href=&#34;http://andrearobertson.com/&#34;target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Andrea&lt;/a&gt; and Donna. Then we went to a really nice zoo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a very long blog post, split into five parts. If you aren&amp;rsquo;t sure how far you&amp;rsquo;ll get, read parts 3 and 4, then 2, then maybe 1. Part 5 is mostly for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../tanzania-1&#34;&gt;1: prep&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;a href=&#34;../tanzania-2&#34;&gt;2: hike&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;a href=&#34;../tanzania-3&#34;&gt;3: summit&lt;/a&gt; - 4: safari - &lt;a href=&#34;../tanzania-5&#34;&gt;5: post-mortem&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;a href=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/trips/kili&#34;target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;slide show (upcoming)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;!-- TODO Slide show anchor link --&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;hitting-the-road&#34;&gt;Hitting the road&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the seven-day mountain trek, the idea of staying in a relaxing country lodge and doing all of our traveling by car sounded great. We weren&amp;rsquo;t out of the woods yet though. During our hike debriefing we were given a tiny bit of vague information about the safari: leaving at 7am tomorrow, don&amp;rsquo;t wear blue or black because of the tsetse flies (surprise!), and &amp;ldquo;pack light&amp;rdquo;. So, still decompressing from the hike, and not knowing quite what to expect, we had to figure out how to repack everything. I had to decide how to distribute all my junk between my duffel (might be stowed somewhere else, with no access), my day pack (might be stuffed in the back of the jeep), and one small bag (can carry all day if I want). Not a big deal, especially with known, mild weather, but still a bit hectic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it turned out, the &amp;ldquo;Bougainvillea Country Lodge&amp;rdquo; was essentially just a nice hotel off the main road, and we had access to all our things as soon as we checked in. I had tried to translate &amp;ldquo;bougainvillea&amp;rdquo;, thinking it was a term for a specific style of remote lodging (something like the &amp;ldquo;Bedouin camp&amp;rdquo; I stayed at in Israel). Actually, it&amp;rsquo;s just a business name, one of hundreds of safari hotels in the area probably.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I woke up at 6, happy to find that all my laundry made it back to my room, and brought all my stuff down to the lobby. For the eight tourists, we had two jeeps, so we had to decide how to split up into two groups. My first thought was that the two cameras, mine and KJ&amp;rsquo;s, should be separated. With the two groups of three, the obvious split was me, Andrea, Donna and Tommy in one jeep, and KJ, Joanne, Joanne, and Chen in the other. We went with this, and later realized we had split the groups as American/British, and also (almost) introvert/extrovert. As we waited in the lobby, Andrea took out her camera, and then I understood why she left it behind during the hike. She brought one of the biggest telephoto lenses that Canon makes; not the best choice of focal length for a mountain hike, and just too big - it&amp;rsquo;s heavier and bulkier than all three of the lenses I brought put together (literally).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/IMG_8554-jeep-exterior.JPG&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Our two safari trucks&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Porters took our duffel bags and daypacks, and loaded them into the trunks of the trucks, at random as far as I could tell. We all piled in, and got on our way. I didn&amp;rsquo;t have a specific picture in my mind of what a safari truck should look like, but I&amp;rsquo;m pretty sure these would have lived up to any expectations. It&amp;rsquo;s a big landrover-looking thing with three rows of passenger seating, a luggage cage in back, two spare tires, and a convertible roof. The inside of the truck was surprisingly similar to the inside of the buildings, in a way. Textured faux stucco walls, what looked like after-market electrical boxes and conduit running around the interior, a couple of full-size electrical outlets set into the wall at knee level. The seats were old and grungy, the arm rests didn&amp;rsquo;t stay in place, and I snagged my pants on a sharp bit of metal sticking out of something. Looking closely at the driver&amp;rsquo;s seat, I noticed two gas gauges on the dashboard, and two gear shifts. I asked about these; there&amp;rsquo;s a second fuel tank because the engine runs on multiple fuels, and the second shifter is for an extreme gear, useful for stuck tires or steep climbs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/IMG_8647-jeep-interior.JPG&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Truck with the roof up&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Earlier, KJ had asked one of the guys if we could make a stop at a native village - it seemed like something he&amp;rsquo;d read about or had recommended, but didn&amp;rsquo;t know much about. The drivers sort of jumped at the opportunity, and the reason became clear soon enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We left the hotel about 7:30, and lost track of the other truck pretty quickly. There was plenty to distract us, between the anticipation of the safari, the sights of the town, and a flood of information from our driver. Joseph started the day very talkatively, which I appreciated; one great reason for travel is to meet and learn from people I otherwise might not. After an hour of driving and hearing his life story, still waiting for specific information about what we would be doing for the next three days, it became exhausting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In light rain, we drove down the main road through town for 30 minutes or an hour before getting to an area that looked more rural. A few things stood out to me - lots of motorbikes, some with multiple people, some with attached umbrellas. Lots of vans with weird decals that sort of reminded me of &lt;a href=&#34;https://sense8.wikia.com/wiki/Van_Damn&#34;target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Van Damn&lt;/a&gt; (actually &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dala_dala&#34;target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;dala dala&lt;/a&gt; I suppose). A big drainage canal right next to the main road. There were some herds of cattle or goats, which got bigger and more frequent the further we went. At one point we saw a group of young men with some sort of traditional apparel, and faces painted black and white, standing on the side of the road. How interesting, we thought. Someone in our truck pointed out that they were essentially a billboard, advertising the &amp;ldquo;native village&amp;rdquo; experience that we would see shortly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/IMG_7545-cattle-crossing.JPG&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Herd crossing&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This whole time, Joseph was telling us quite a story. Safari driving is his side job, during the tourist season. The rest of the year, he works as an anti-poaching park ranger. Apparently, there is a poaching season, opposite tourist season, and they are not a big problem outside of that time. It had never occurred to me, but I suppose it makes sense; poachers want to hide, tourists want clear and comfortable weather for their safaris. He shared quite a bit about that experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Poaching is a pervasive thing, and the picture of the whole situation that I got from Joseph has some obvious parallels to organized crime in the US. It seems to be deeply connected to corruption, entrenched ways of life, and the economy. Many animals, people and groups are part of the poaching ecosystem. Ivory and rhino horns are maybe the worst of it, demand for the materials driving the hunting of endangered species by professionals. Perhaps more understandable are the local people just trying to feed their village with whatever animals and methods make sense. There&amp;rsquo;s a market aspect as well; some bushmen may not participate in poaching directly, but are happy to trade with poachers for meat. Joseph said this is how poachers get their hands on poison arrows, the scariest thing to face as an anti-poaching ranger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/IMG_8776-joseph.JPG&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Our safari driver and guide, Joseph&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joseph grew up in a village that depended on poaching. It&amp;rsquo;s a normal way to acquire food, and status. When his father was caught after killing a leopard, he was given an ultimatum: go to prison for some lengthy period, or sacrifice a son to be trained as an anti-poacher. The choice becomes obvious, when the son is only one of several family members, and there is no one else to provide for the rest of them. This punishment struck me as cruel, but effective and poetic. It&amp;rsquo;s also absolute; after the decision was made, the village rejected Joseph entirely. He lost his home, his family, his friends, his fiancee. He resented it for a long time, but somehow his education opened his eyes to how destructive poaching is; he feels that he is in the right place now, and is happily married with a child.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was the short version; he fed us the details non-stop while we listened incredulously. When we finally had a break, Donna turned to us almost in tears and said it was too much, she couldn&amp;rsquo;t handle hearing this tragic life story any more. We were surprised to have stopped driving; it seemed like we&amp;rsquo;d been on the road too long already, and we still hadn&amp;rsquo;t made it anywhere. Somehow we had passed the other truck, and we&amp;rsquo;d been driving slowly so they could catch up. We were all hungry by this point, so we asked for our boxed lunches, and ate awkwardly with flimsy plasticware as we continued driving. At some point in the early morning, we stopped at another hotel, where we sat around and talked about the safari briefly, then left with the same trucks and the same drivers. In retrospect, maybe we were waiting for the rain to subside.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/IMG_7621-maasai-fire.JPG&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Firestarter&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Around 11am we arrived at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maasai_people&#34;target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Maasai&lt;/a&gt; village. We pulled in to a parking lot just off the highway, and a group of boys wearing bright plaid shawls swarmed to greet us. I took the opportunity to rummage through my bag for whatever, and the rest of the group went off to start the tour. I didn&amp;rsquo;t hear the first couple minutes of greeting or explanation, though I doubt I missed much. The tribe started a sort of singing and dancing ceremony, and tried to pull some of us into it. I think I refused first, then KJ tried to refuse but gave in, maybe feeling responsible for our being there. He had to dance in a circle with a shawl and a pole, and he felt super awkward about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/IMG_7574-maasai-dance-kj.JPG&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;KJ the dancer&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next they circled up and started another ceremony, which I can only describe as a standing high jump contest. Fortunately they didn&amp;rsquo;t push us into this event, but they did grab a couple more of us to stand around and look pretty. Next up was a demonstration of their firemaking system, spinning a stick in a wooden base by hand, and using it to light some straw kindling. After that, we were each given a tour of a small hut, made from mud, dung, sticks, and grass. I laid down on the cowhide bed that took up most of the floor, and my guy kinda insisted on using my phone to take a photo of me there. We stopped at the kindergarten where a room full of tiny cute children sang a song for us. This was one of a few times I wanted to take a photo, but felt odd doing it. Finally, they herded us into their gift shop, a big clearing ringed with tables full of souvenirs that I had no interest in. I did, however, have too many Tanzanian shillings in my pocket, so I bought a couple of things. When I started looking like I&amp;rsquo;d buy something, they surrounded me like prey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/IMG_7602-maasai-donna.JPG&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Donna, standing around looking pretty&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andrea quietly said to me &amp;ldquo;First we went to the people zoo, now we go to the animal zoo&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;. I nodded in agreement at the sentiment that the whole experience was offputting. I remarked about how uncomfortable I had felt taking photos at the village, or sticking my camera out of the safari truck while driving through town. I don&amp;rsquo;t feel too bad about it; we paid $50 per vehicle for a 30-minute tour, ending with an overpriced gift shop. If they&amp;rsquo;re comfortable with the exchange, I don&amp;rsquo;t know why we shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be. Regardless, I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t exactly recommend it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;day-1-lake-manyara&#34;&gt;Day 1: Lake Manyara&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alright, on to the good part: the animals. I took about 1200 photos over the course of the three-day safari, and I&amp;rsquo;ve pared that down to the top 100 or so. You can see all of those in the (upcoming) slide show, I&amp;rsquo;ll just include a handful of the best ones in this post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- TODO slide show#anchor link to day 1 --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a bewildering morning, we arrived at the entrance to Lake Manyara National Park around noon, waited a few minutes for paperwork or something, and finally got started on the animal-viewing part of the day. Although we didn&amp;rsquo;t see the tree-climbing lions that live in this park, we did see plenty of animals. Not knowing what to expect of the safari, I was pleasantly surprised at how much there was to look at. Rather than an exercise in spotting camouflaged critters hiding in the distance, we saw animals everywhere, in large numbers. Of course there were some that were further away or harder to spot, but our driver/guide was incredibly good at this. I suppose when you spend half the year tracking poachers, skills like that are key. Drivers also communicate via radio, and they are happy to alert each other to upcoming animal sights. Even knowing that, his abilities were impressive. Mostly, the sightings were so, so close, so well-timed, that we had to joke about the animals being delivered to our route on schedule.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what did we see at Manyara? Baboons, mostly. Also elephants, giraffes, hippos, and lots of birds, but there were so many baboons. We saw them in small groups and in big troops, we saw them sitting around doing nothing, fighting with each other, drinking from a stream, and, yes, even mating. We probably saw a thousand baboons, in dozens of different groups, over the course of the drive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/IMG_7811-baboons-and-more.JPG&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Baboons, eagle, water buffalo?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We saw plenty at Manyara, and I got photos of lots of different animals. From my childhood training in Amazon Trail, I know the goal is to get one good photo of each species, and then identify each one, but I&amp;rsquo;m not all the way there yet. The safari section of the slide show has 1) all the interesting action shots, and 2) all the different species I got. I&amp;rsquo;ve tried to identify some of the ones that aren&amp;rsquo;t obvious, but I don&amp;rsquo;t have the patience to figure out all of it. Especially the birds, the few I managed to identify after the fact were painstaking, and I&amp;rsquo;m not sure how to go about the rest effectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a list of some of the mammals we saw on day 1: elephant, giraffe, hippo, zebra, baboon, vervet monkey (blue balls), dik-dik, a variety of antelope, wildebeest, warthog. Birds include: eagle, egret, grey-crowned crane, pelican, stork, ibis, but there were dozens of bird species here, more than the next two parks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/IMG_8040-fancy-giraffe.JPG&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fancy giraffe&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first day of the safari was fun, and it was good to get a feel for what the trips for the next few days would be like. For example, we learned that it was super dusty all the time, and breathing sucks if you haven&amp;rsquo;t been covering your nose. We were all glad that it was over after a few hours, especially Tommy who had spent half the drive sleeping in the back seat. We left the park and headed for the place we&amp;rsquo;d be sleeping for the next two nights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;bougainvillea-country-lodge&#34;&gt;Bougainvillea Country Lodge&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stella Maris was fine - a place to sleep and eat while preparing for the trek - but nothing special. Bougainvillea was picturesque and full of amenities, just the kind of place you&amp;rsquo;d expect to stay for a relaxing vacation, or a spa day. Roomy cottages surrounded a lush central courtyard, full of a variety of exotic-looking plants, and a pool in the middle. It was an oasis of green in an otherwise brown world. Many of the buildings we had seen, including both previous hotels, looked like they were built by amateurs, or updated and patched so much that nothing quite fit anymore. There&amp;rsquo;s nothing wrong with this, of course. It just meant that Bougainvillea stood out as well-built and well-maintained.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/IMG_8543-lodge-pool.JPG&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Our pool and garden&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not too into spa stuff, but there was a whole suite of services available; I think I was the only one of our group who didn&amp;rsquo;t get a massage that first day. Trying to schedule all seven of the massages as soon as possible was a challenge, watching them sort that out was amusing. I don&amp;rsquo;t recall what the other options were, but I&amp;rsquo;m sure Tommy does, he ditched the second day and probably ordered one of everything on the spa menu back at the lodge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the physical structures at the place stood out as more professionally built, the service stood out as&amp;hellip; a bit off, I suppose. It felt like the waitstaff had been trained on how to be attentive to guests in a way that westerners would appreciate, but they did it by watching an old film, and then practicing on mannequins. Early on, one guy started a conversation with me. He remembered my name from that, and throughout our stay, he would make a point of addressing me by name, for no reason. This might sound petty, but just imagine having your train of thought randomly interrupted with &amp;ldquo;Hi Alan! What&amp;rsquo;s up?&amp;rdquo; while you&amp;rsquo;re just hanging out, relaxing or eating dinner. I appreciated the effort, but the execution was lacking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/IMG_8546-lodge-drinks.JPG&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Just chillin&#39;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dinner was very nice. I got a peek at the menu earlier in the day, tried to decide what to order. When we all sat down to eat, I realized it was essentially a prix fixe meal, but served in a way I&amp;rsquo;ve never seen before. They didn&amp;rsquo;t bring out plates for each of us, and they didn&amp;rsquo;t have a buffet set up. They did a weird hybrid of those two styles, where servers would each bring out two big serving bowls of two different dishes, one in each hand, and hold them precariously near your plate (but not over it) while you serve yourself. It seemed inefficient and messy, but it didn&amp;rsquo;t stop me from enjoying the food.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I remembered our airport shuttle driver telling us about something called banana beer. I asked his favorite type, and he gave me a brand - mgembe or something - so I asked for this at the hotel bar. The bartender just laughed, and said they didn&amp;rsquo;t have it there. &amp;ldquo;You have to go out there&amp;rdquo; he said, and nodded toward the main road. Not suitable for my delicate western palate, I guess. I ordered the cocktail special instead, and it was basically juice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/IMG_8076-lodge-dinner.JPG&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dinner at our reserved table&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I woke up early after the first night, I found some reason to wander around outside. Coming back into the room, I noticed bees, all over the door, and the wall next to it. Some of them clumped together, none of them moving. Sleeping, I guess? It freaked me out a little, but I got over it, and they didn&amp;rsquo;t flinch when I opened the door.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second evening, as we sat in the courtyard, one of the waitstaff came over and started talking to Tommy, making a blunt segue into a request for money. I don&amp;rsquo;t recall the details, something about tuition I&amp;rsquo;m sure. I watched for a full five minutes or so as Tommy listened, and turned him down more politely. He offered to do some research and connect the guy with some local charities, and then struggled to figure out how to successfully trade contact info. I got the impression that the guy was breaking a rule, and maybe he trusted Tommy to be cool about it, after spending some time together earlier in the day. Again, a bit odd, but gotta respect the hustle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;day-2-ngorongoro-crater&#34;&gt;Day 2: Ngorongoro crater&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;!-- TODO slide show anchor link --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;video autoplay muted loop width=700px src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/crater-flyover.webm&#34;&gt;&lt;/video&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;100 square miles, 2000 ft deep&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/2018-09-29-15.16.04-crater-pano.jpg&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The whole crater from the rim&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ngorongoro was clearly the best park of the three we visited. The animals and the action of course, but also the geology. Ngorongoro crater is &amp;ldquo;the world&amp;rsquo;s largest inactive, intact and unfilled volcanic caldera&amp;rdquo;, and I had no idea I&amp;rsquo;d be able to appreciate that so well in person. Approaching the crater puts you on a ridge for a few minutes, until you reach the turn down into the crater. This part isn&amp;rsquo;t so different from driving down a switchback-heavy mountain road, especially in the morning with fog limiting the visibility. At the crater floor, we got under the fog, and started to see the walls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;video autoplay muted loop width=700px src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/MVI_8535-crater.webm&#34;&gt;&lt;/video&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Driving around on the crater rim&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later on, winding around the roads inside the crater, we would approach the walls, which look like vertical walls of forest. The crater isn&amp;rsquo;t quite a circle, but near enough that the walls were visible in every direction when the fog lifted. Ascending to the rim when we left was my favorite part of the drive. With the fog gone, and slowly climbing, I could see the entire crater for a few minutes. I stood up in the convertible roof the whole way up. It&amp;rsquo;s incredible, and I&amp;rsquo;ll never capture in words what it feels like to see this thing in person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/IMG_8505-crater-rim-270.JPG&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;My best photo showing the rim wall&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were so many animals inside the crater, thousands of individuals among dozens of herds and flocks, of many different species. Some of them put on a great show for us. I figured the most interesting thing we might see would be a lion kill. We didn&amp;rsquo;t quite get that, but we saw the next act. We spotted lions a few times throughout the day, and then Donna pointed out what she thought was a tiger at first glance. A second later, it came into clearer view, and we all realized it was a zebra - black stripes against bloodied white - dead on the ground. Two lions sat around nearby, watching their kill. Just one in a long line of trucks, we stopped to watch, luckily with a great vantage point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/IMG_8320-lions-zebra.JPG&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Guarding the kill&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We couldn&amp;rsquo;t have driven through the line of stopped trucks if we&amp;rsquo;d wanted, which was fine because there was &lt;em&gt;drama&lt;/em&gt; unfolding right in front of us. We stayed there for an hour, and I took about 200 photos of this sequence of events. The lions are the only hunters common to the crater floor (I think), so presumably it&amp;rsquo;s their kill. They&amp;rsquo;re not the only meat-eaters though, so they need to protect it. The most obvious contender was the pair of jackals, sneakily spiraling in on the carcass. Actually, it turned out to be a pack of at least six jackals, which we realized as we slowly spotted them watching from a distance. On the other side of the road was a hyena, not as quick as the jackals, taking his time. And there are always eyes watching from high above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/IMG_8337-lion-chasing.JPG&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Big guy has had enough&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The stage is set, the players are ready, what&amp;rsquo;s next? First, the jackals test the lions&#39; limits, darting in and looking for an opening. One of them makes it to the zebra, and starts picking at it, face down for only a fraction of a second before bringing his eyes back up to scan for the threat of the lions - seems like a tough way to eat. He gets a few bites like this before the female gets annoyed and charges the carcass. The jackal backs off a bit, the male lion comes in, and the jackal gets back to circling. They test each other a bit more, and the pack strategy wins as one jackal manages to rip off a big hunk of meat and runs away with it. Two jackals start pulling on this piece from opposite sides, fighting each other or working together to shred it, and then they pull back, satisfied with their prize.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;video autoplay muted loop width=700px src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/MVI_8280-jackal.webm&#34;&gt;&lt;/video&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;How to eat like a scavenger&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lions start picking at the carcass, and the male does something stupid, prompting the female to roar and paw at him, like she&amp;rsquo;s telling him to get out of her way so she can eat in peace. Meanwhile, the jackals&#39; chunk of meat is drawing attention, as it&amp;rsquo;s now far enough from the lions to be safe for a vulture to swoop down and steal a piece for herself. The hyena is still biding his time. Three levels of scavenging strategy, demonstrated in live action for us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/IMG_8355-jackals-fighting.JPG&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Working together?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had to switch to present tense there, it just feels better for the play-by-play of the circle of life. After all this, the male lion headed for the section of road we were parked on. Not that the action was far away, but he came straight to the road, and laid down on the ground right in between two trucks, five feet away from those passengers, and maybe 50 feet from us. He hung out there for a bit, trapping both of those adjacent trucks, and everyone got some closeup photos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/IMG_8427-lion-road.JPG&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why did the lion cross the road?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This episode was clearly the high point of the safari. We also saw dozens of other animals, but a list of species feels underwhelming, comparatively. For the sake of posterity, here goes: we saw other lion packs laying around, antelope, buffalo, zebra, elephants, wildebeest, a handful of hyenas, hippos with little white birds on them, guineas, kori bustard, lots more birds I can&amp;rsquo;t identify. We were surprised to see flamingos, and surprised to see just how big an ostrich is. Also surprised at just how ugly a warthog is. We did see one rhino, a gray lump laying on the ground so far away that I basically had to take Joseph&amp;rsquo;s word for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We saw lots of elephants, at least a few every day. It was at Ngorongoro that I got some close-up views of them eating acacia trees. That name sounded familiar, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t know anything about the trees. The branches are covered in 2-3 inch thorns, and elephants just wrap their trunk around a branch, rip it off, and stuff it in their mouth, thorns and all. This was astounding to me. Later, I learned there&amp;rsquo;s an interesting &lt;a href=&#34;https://indianapublicmedia.org/amomentofscience/acacias-ants-elephants/&#34;target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;relationship&lt;/a&gt; between acacia, ants that live in the thorns, and herbivores that eat the trees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/IMG_8615-elephant-acacia.JPG&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Yummy thorns&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think it was some time during day 2 that I started noticing Joseph&amp;rsquo;s behavior more. He drives, he spots animals, and he tells passengers about the environment and the animals, so he has plenty to do. But when he sees something good and stops for it, he has an unpredictable amount of time to kill, waiting until the passengers are bored. Joseph would just sit still in the driver&amp;rsquo;s seat, staring down at his lap. I couldn&amp;rsquo;t help feeling bad for him. On the other hand, it seems like a decent gig, at least for a driving job. As for us tourists, the main downside was the continued exposure to dust, making breathing less and less fun as the day went on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;day-3-tarangire&#34;&gt;Day 3: Tarangire&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;!-- TODO slide show anchor link --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/tarangire-track.png&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Our track from day 3, not quite as interesting as the crater&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On day 3, we brought all our bags when we left in the morning, as we&amp;rsquo;d be driving straight to the airport afterward. We said goodbye to the lodge, and headed for Tarangire National park, an expanse of river valley and swamp. As fun as the safari was, sitting in the jeep all day was a bit tiring, so I followed Andrea&amp;rsquo;s lead and got a red bull from the park cafe, to drink later in the day. The order we visited these parks was perfect; the shortest and least interesting (but not bad!) first, sort of a half rest day, the best and longest second, and the middle one last. It&amp;rsquo;s too bad the logistics prevented Tommy from sitting out on day 1 instead of day 2, but he still got to see some good stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, we had some mystery time to kill, so I wandered around, and found some decorative animal bones, including an enormous elephant skull. Even knowing how big the animal is, it&amp;rsquo;s still astounding to see one of their skulls up close. We also realized that it&amp;rsquo;s the shape of the skull that makes an elephant look like it&amp;rsquo;s smiling all the time. I found some sort of observation tower, built around a baobab tree, and climbed to the top. There was nothing but scrubland as far I could see. Compared to the previous parks, it was a very dry place. Have I mentioned how dusty it was? It was super dusty at Tarangire. By day 3, my breathing was seriously starting to suffer; I ended up wearing a full face cover most of the day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/IMG_8576-watering-hole.JPG&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Watering hole&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a few minutes, we got started. Of course, the novelty of seeing these enormous herds of animals was beginning to wear off, so day 3 wasn&amp;rsquo;t quite as exciting. There were still some stand-out moments, of course. There were more watering-hole scenes in this park, often with a few different types of animals sharing the space peacefully. The most interesting flora of the day was the baobab tree, huge and alien. We would pass one every minute or so, and Joseph told us to watch for leopards; we didn&amp;rsquo;t spot any. He told us that baobabs produce large, weird fruits, which we also didn&amp;rsquo;t see. I liked Joseph&amp;rsquo;s accent; &amp;ldquo;baobab&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;leopard&amp;rdquo; stood out particularly. I would have said &amp;ldquo;bay-oh-bab&amp;rdquo;, he says &amp;ldquo;bao-bab&amp;rdquo;, pronouncing &amp;ldquo;bao&amp;rdquo; like the Chinese bun. His pronunciation of leopard isn&amp;rsquo;t easily representible in English, but it&amp;rsquo;s sort of like &amp;ldquo;Lay-yoh-pard&amp;rdquo;, but the first two syllables are combined into one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/IMG_2004-donna-elephant.jpg&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Donna got this perfect photo of a mother and baby&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We saw huge termite mounds all over the park, and later we noticed these odd, tall black rods, that looked like carefully constructed towers of dirt. When we asked Joseph and he told us they were just bare palm tree trunks, we felt silly. Circling around on some tangled roads, we spotted a group of 20-30 elephants. Trying to find a way to get closer, we drove down a bank toward some stagnant water. As we got closer, a plague of tsetse flies descended upon us. We had met some of these guys previously, and knew they were more annoying than dangerous. We&amp;rsquo;d all been bitten a few times, it&amp;rsquo;s a small, sharp pain, it goes away quickly, and it&amp;rsquo;s ultimately less irritating than a mosquito bite. When there are hundreds of them flying around inside your vehicle, it&amp;rsquo;s a different story. We all freaked out, I covered my face, Andrea and Donna started waving their hands around like crazy. Joseph did NOT intend for this to happen, so he turned around and sped out of there as quickly as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/IMG_8731-monkey-thief.JPG&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Monkey thief&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lunch was entertaining, thanks to the monkeys that have learned from exposure to tourists. As we walked into our little lunch spot, we saw monkeys everywhere, and within minutes we heard someone yelling after they realized one had stolen some part of their lunch. The seating area was surrounded by monkeys, and they&amp;rsquo;re much quicker and more motivated than lazy humans. Fortunately we made it through lunch mostly unmolested.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I headed back to the truck, I spotted a mother monkey with a baby clinging to her belly, and started taking photos. We slowly approached each other, until we were just a few feet apart. She stood still and posed for me, while I took a couple dozen photos. I had time to frame the shot, change lenses, fiddle with settings. This may have been the best excuse I&amp;rsquo;ve ever had to use the articulated screen on my camera, holding it out at arms length for an even closer shot, without getting unnervingly close to a wild animal in Africa. I doubt she would have done anything mean, it looked like she was working for tips.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/IMG_8767-monkey-mama-270.JPG&#34;
        alt/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Monkey mama&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of our time driving in the parks, our two trucks were loosely together, sometimes right next to us, sometimes way out of sight. This, I think, gave our drivers more chances to spot animals. This worked well on day 3, when the other truck found some lazy lions laying around under a tree, and called us over to see them. If we thought this was sort of mild compared to the previous day, the next sight more than made up for it. We stopped close to a dead wildebeest - maybe a kill, maybe not - surrounded by vultures. The smell was powerful and bad. Another example of the variety of animals we saw together, there were some ducks loitering nearby, and a marabou stork (AKA the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marabou_stork&#34;target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;undertaker bird&lt;/a&gt;) stalked behind the scene like the boss checking how the work was coming along. After watching for a few minutes, the ladies&#39; delicate senses of smell compelled us to move along.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;video autoplay muted loop width=700px src=&#34;https://alanbernstein.net/blog-static/img
/tanzania/MVI_8818-driving.webm&#34;&gt;&lt;/video&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cruisin&#39;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../tanzania-2#problems&#34;&gt;Back to part 2 - the hike&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--
https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Category:Birds_of_Lake_Manyara_National_Park
http://www.exoticbirding.com/tanzania/manyara/checklist.html
- golden crested crane
- stork
- ibis
- antelope is a &#34;wastebasket taxon&#34;
--&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>